<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Madrigales. The triumphes of Oriana, to 5. and 6. voices: composed by divers severall aucthors. / Newly published by Thomas Morley batcheler of musick, and one of the gentlemen of her Maiesties honorable chappell.</title>
            <title>Triumphes of Oriana</title>
            <author>Morley, Thomas, 1557-1603?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 160KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 90 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B00445</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">44920538_173820</idno>
  <idno type="VID">173820</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2248555128</idno>
  <idno type="STC">STC 18130.5</idno>
  <idno type="STC">ESTC S110049</idno>
  
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B00445)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 173820)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 560:2-3, 1075:2, 2100:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Madrigales. The triumphes of Oriana, to 5. and 6. voices: composed by divers severall aucthors. / Newly published by Thomas Morley batcheler of musick, and one of the gentlemen of her Maiesties honorable chappell.</title>
                  <title>Triumphes of Oriana</title>
                  <author>Morley, Thomas, 1557-1603?</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[176] p. in 6 parts : music.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Thomas Este, the assigne of Thomas Morley.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>In London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1601.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: Pts. 1-4, 6: [blank]² B-D⁴, E²; pt. 5: [blank]², B⁴, C².</note>
                  <note>Parts: cantus, altus, tenor, quintus, sextus, and bassus.</note>
                  <note>"Cum priuilegio Regiæ Maiestatis."</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of originals in: Folger Shakespeare Library (560:2-3, altus, sextus) and Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Madrigals (Music) --  England.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Part-songs --  England.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-05 </date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-05 </date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:173820:1"/>
                  <p>CANTVS.</p>
                  <p>MADRIGALES The Triumphes of Oriana, to 5. and 6. voices: com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posed by diuers seuerall <hi>aucthors.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Newly published by Thomas Morley Batcheler of Musick, and one of the gentlemen of her</hi> Maiesties honorable Chappell.</p>
                  <p>1601.</p>
                  <p>IN LONDON PRINTED BY THOMAS ESTE, the assigne of Thomas Morley.</p>
                  <p>¶ Cum priuilegio Regiae Maiestatis.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="table_of_contents">
                  <pb facs="tcp:173820:2"/>
                  <head>¶ The Table of all the Madrigales contained in these bookes, vvith the names of their seuerall authors.</head>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Songs of 5. parts.</head>
                     <list>
                        <item>Hence Stars you dazell but the sight. <hi>Michaell Este.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>VVIth Angells face and brightnesse. I <hi>Daniell Norcome.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Lightly she whipped o're y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> dales. II <hi>Iohn Mundy Batcheler of Musick</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Long liue faire <hi>Oriana.</hi> III <hi>Ellis Gibbons.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>All creatures now are merry. IIII <hi>Iohn Benet.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Faire <hi>Oriana</hi> beauties Queene. V <hi>Iohn Hilton. Batcheler of Musick</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>The Nymphs and shepherds danced. VI <hi>George Marson. Batch. of Musick</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Calme was the Aire. VII <hi>Richard Carlton. Batch. of Musick</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Thus bonny bootes the birth day. VIII <hi>Iohn Holmes.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Sing shepherds all. IX <hi>Richard Nicolson.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>The Faunes and Satirs tripping. X <hi>Thomas Tomkins.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Come gentle swaines. XI <hi>Michaell Cauendish.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Withdraw your selues yee shepherds. XII <hi>William Cobbold.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Arise awake you silly shepherds sleping. XIII <hi>Thomas Morley Batch. of Musick</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Song of 6. parts.</head>
                     <list>
                        <item>Faire Nymphes I heard one telling. XIIII <hi>Iohn Farmer.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>The lady <hi>Oriana.</hi> XV <hi>Iohn Wilby.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Hark! hark, did you euer heare &amp;c. XVI <hi>Thomas Hunt. Batch. of Musick</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>As <hi>Ʋesta</hi> was from <hi>Latmos</hi> hill &amp;c. XVII <hi>Thomas Weelks.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Faire <hi>Orian</hi> in the morne. XVIII <hi>Iohn Milton.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Round about her Charret &amp;c. XIX <hi>Ellis Gibbons.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>With Angells face and brightnesse. XX <hi>George Kirbye.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Faire <hi>Oriana</hi> seeming to wink at folly. XXI <hi>Robert Iones.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Faire <hi>Citharea</hi> presents her Doues &amp;c. XXII <hi>Iohn Lisley.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Hard by a Christall fountaine. XXIII <hi>Thomas Morley. Batch. of Musick</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Come blessed Byrd &amp;c. XXIIII <hi>Edward Iohnson. Batch. of Musick</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
               <div type="dedication">
                  <pb facs="tcp:173820:2"/>
                  <head>TO THE RIGHT HO<seg rend="sup">norable</seg>. THE LORD Charles Howard <hi>Earle of Notingham, Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron</hi> of <hi>Effingham,</hi> Knight of the Noble order of the <hi>Garter,</hi> Lord high <hi>Admirall</hi> of <hi>England, Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and <hi>Wales, &amp;c.</hi> And one of her Majesties most honorable Priuie Counsell.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>RIGHT HO<seg rend="sup">norab</seg>.</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Haue aduentured to dedicate these few discordant tunes to be censured by the ingenious disposition of your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ships Honorable rare perfection, perswading my selfe, that these labours, composed by me and others, (as in the sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uey hereof, your Lordship may well perceiue) may not by any meanes passe, without the malignitie of some maliti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous <hi>Momus,</hi> whose malice (being as toothsome as the <hi>Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders</hi> sting) couched in the progres of a wayfayring mans passage, might make him retire though almost at his iourneyes end. Two speci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all <hi>Motiues</hi> haue imbouldened me (right Honorable) in this my proceeding. First, for that I consider, that as the body cannot bee without the shadow: so <hi>Homer</hi> (the Prince of Poets) may not be without a <hi>Zoilist:</hi> The second &amp; last is (the most forcible motiue) I know, (not onely by report, but also by experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment) your Lordship, to bee not onely <hi>Philomusus</hi> a louer of the <hi>Muses,</hi> and of learning: but <hi>Philomathes,</hi> a personage alway desirous, (though in all Arts sufficiently skilfull) to come to a more high perfection or <hi>Summum bonum.</hi> I will not trouble your Lordship with to to tedious circumstances, onely I humbly intreat your Lordship (in the name of many) to patronage this work with no lesse acceptance, then I with a willing and kinde hart dedicate it. So shall I think the <hi>initium</hi> of this worke not onely happely begun, but to bee <hi>finited</hi> with a more happie period.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Your Honours deuoted in all dutie, Thomas Morley.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div n="cantus" type="musical_part">
                  <div type="songs_of_five_parts">
                     <div type="song">
                        <pb facs="tcp:173820:3"/>
                        <head>Of 5. CANTVS.</head>
                        <byline>Michaell Este.</byline>
                        <p>
                           <gap reason="music">
                              <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                           </gap> HEnce Stars, you dazel but the sight, you teach to grope by night, you teach: ij. you dazell but the sight, you teach to grope by night, you: ij See heere the shepherds Star, Then <hi>Phebus</hi> wipt his eyes, and <hi>Zephir</hi> cleer'd the Skies, and: ij in sweet accented cries, in: ij. Then sang the shepherds &amp; Nymphs of <hi>Dia╌na,</hi> Nymphs: ij. Long liue faire <hi>O╌ria╌na,</hi> Long: ij. Long: ij. Long: ij. Long: ij. <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na,</hi> Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>This song being sent to late, and all the other printed, I plast it before the rest, rather then to leaue it out.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="1" type="song">
                        <pb facs="tcp:173820:3"/>
                        <head>Of 5. I. CANTVS.</head>
                        <byline>Daniell Norcome. </byline>
                        <p>
                           <gap reason="music">
                              <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                           </gap> WIth Angels face and brightnesse, ij. &amp; orient hew, faire <hi>Ori╌a╌na</hi> shining, with nimble foote she tripped, ij. o're hils, and mountaines, o're hills &amp; moūtaines, ij. at last in dale she rested: this is that maiden <hi>Queene</hi> of the Fayrie land, of the Fairie land, with scepter in her hand, ij. the Faunes and Satires dauncing, daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing, did shew their nimble nimble lightnes, ij. Faire <hi>Nais</hi> and the Nimphs did leaue their bowers, did: ij. &amp; brought their baskets full of hearbs &amp; flowers. Thē sang y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> sheperds &amp; Nimphs of Di╌ana, ij. Lōg liue, Lōg liue faire O╌ri╌ana. ij. ij. ij.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="2" type="song">
                        <pb facs="tcp:173820:4"/>
                        <head>Of 5. II. CANTVS.</head>
                        <byline>Iohn Mundy.</byline>
                        <p>
                           <gap reason="music">
                              <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                           <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>Ightly she whipped o're y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> dales, o're the dales, ij. o're the dales, making the woods proud, making the woods proud with her presence, with her presence, Gently she trode the flowres, gently trode the flowres, ij. the flowres &amp; they as gētly kist her tender feet, The birds in their best lan╌guage bad her welcome, being proud that <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na</hi> heard their song: y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> cloue foot Satires singing, made Musick to the Faunes a daun╌cing, &amp; both to gether with an emphasis, sang <hi>O╌ri╌a╌nas</hi> prai╌ses, ij. ij. whilst the aioyning woods with melody, with melody, ij. did entertain their sweet sweet
<pb facs="tcp:173820:4"/>
                           <gap reason="music">
                              <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                           </gap> harmony, sweet harmony. Then sang the sheperds and Nimphes of <hi>Di╌a╌na,</hi> the Nimphes of <hi>Dia╌na,</hi> ij. ij. Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na,</hi> ij. ij. ij. ij. faire <hi>Ori╌a╌na.</hi> ij.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="3" type="song">
                        <pb facs="tcp:173820:5"/>
                        <head>Of 5. III. CANTVS.</head>
                        <byline>Ellis Gibbons.</byline>
                        <p>
                           <gap reason="music">
                              <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                           </gap> LOng liue faire <hi>Ori╌a╌na,</hi> Heark, did you euer heare so sweet a singing, They sing young Loue to waken, The Nimphs vn╌to the woods, ij. their Queene are bring╌ing, Ther was a note well taken, O good, Hark, how ioyful╌ly tis ditti'd, how ioyfully, how: ij. how: ij. how ioyfully tis ditti'd, how ioyfully, ij. tis dit╌ti'd, A Queene &amp; Song most excellent╌ly fitted, I ne╌uer saw a fai╌rer, I neuer heard nor saw a rarer, Then sing ye Shepherds and Nimphs of <hi>Di╌a╌na,</hi> Nimphs of <hi>Di╌a╌na,</hi> Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na,</hi> ij. Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na,</hi> ij. ij. Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na, O╌ri╌a╌na,</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="4" type="song">
                        <pb facs="tcp:173820:5"/>
                        <head>Of 5. IIII. CANTVS.</head>
                        <byline>Iohn Benet.</byline>
                        <p>
                           <gap reason="music">
                              <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                           </gap> ALL cre'tures now are merry merry {repeat} minded, are merry merry {repeat} {repeat} {repeat} {repeat} {repeat} {repeat} minded, The shepherds daughters playing, {repeat} The Nimphes are Fa la laing, {repeat} The Nimphs are Fa la la la la-ing, Yond bugle was well win╌ded, At <hi>O╌rianaes</hi> presence each thing smi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth, the flowers themselues discouer, {repeat} Birds ouer hir do ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, Musicke the time beguileth {repeat} See wher she comes, {repeat} with flowry garlands crowned, Queene of all queenes renowned, {repeat} Then sang the shepherds &amp; Nimphes of <hi>Diana,</hi> Nimphes of <hi>Diana,</hi> long liue faire <hi>Ori╌a╌na, O╌ri╌a╌na,</hi> faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na,</hi> Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="5" type="song">
                        <pb facs="tcp:173820:6"/>
                        <head>Of 5. V. CANTVS.</head>
                        <byline>Iohn Hilton,</byline>
                        <p>
                           <gap reason="music">
                              <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                           </gap> FAire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na</hi> beauties Queene, beauties Queene, faire <hi>Ori╌a╌na,</hi> faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na,</hi> beauties Queene, {repeat} Tripped a long the verdant greene, tripped &amp;c. The Faunes &amp; Satires, {repeat} running out running out, Skipped and danced {repeat} round about, {repeat} round a╌bout, round about: Flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra forsooke hir painted bowrs, forsooke hir pain╌ted bowres, And made a Coronet of flowres, of flowers, and &amp;c. a Coronet of flowres. Then sang the Nimphs of chast <hi>Di╌a╌na,</hi> {repeat} Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌ana,</hi> faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na,</hi> faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na,</hi> Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na.</hi> Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="6" type="song">
                        <pb facs="tcp:173820:6"/>
                        <head>Of 5. VI. CANTVS.</head>
                        <byline>George Marson.</byline>
                        <p>
                           <gap reason="music">
                              <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                           </gap> THe Nimphs and shepheards daunced, La╌uoltos in a da╌zy tapstred vally, loue loue from their face lamps glaunced, Till wantonly they dally, Then in a Rose bankt, a Rose bankt ally, Bright Maiestie aduanced, {repeat} {repeat} A crowne grac't Virgin whom all people honor, all people honor, They leaue their sport amazed, Runne all to looke vpon hir, runne all to looke vpon hir, A moment scarce they gazed, Ere beauties splendor all their eies had da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed, all &amp;c. desire to see yet euer fixed on hir, Then sang the Shepherds &amp; Nimphs of <hi>Di╌ana,</hi> Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌ana,</hi> {repeat} Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na.</hi> faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na.</hi> Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="7" type="song">
                        <pb facs="tcp:173820:7"/>
                        <head>Of 5. VII. CANTVS.</head>
                        <byline>Richard Carlton.</byline>
                        <p>
                           <gap reason="music">
                              <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                           </gap> CAlme was the aire, {repeat} and cleere the skye, Faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na</hi> passing by, Ouer the downes to I╌da plains ij. Wher heau'n born si╌sters with their traines, Did all attend hir sacred beauty, Striuing to excell in du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, Satirs and Nimphs dauncing together, together, Shepherds triumphing {repeat} flocking thether, Seeing their sou'raigne mistris ther, their &amp;c. That kept their flocks &amp; them from feare, That kept: &amp;c. That kept: &amp;c. With hie strayn'd voice, &amp; harts re╌ioyce, reioyce. Thus sang the sheperds &amp; Nimphs of <hi>Di╌a╌na,</hi> Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na,</hi> {repeat} {repeat} Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="8" type="song">
                        <pb facs="tcp:173820:7"/>
                        <head>Of 5. VIII. CANTVS.</head>
                        <byline> Iohn Holmes.</byline>
                        <p>
                           <gap reason="music">
                              <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                           </gap> THus bonny╌boots the birth day cele╌brated, celebrated, Of her his Lady dee╌rest, his Lady deerest, Faire <hi>O╌ria╌na,</hi> which to his hart was neerest, The Nymphs &amp; shepherds feasted. With clowted creame, with clowted creame were, and to sing re╌quested, {repeat} Loe heere the faire created (Quoth he) the worlds chiefe goddesse, Sing then, the &amp;c. for she is Bonny-bootes sweet Mistres. Then sang the shepherds &amp; Nymphs of <hi>Diana,</hi> Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na. O╌ri╌a╌na,</hi> Long: &amp;c. <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na.</hi> Long: &amp;c. <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na.</hi> Long &amp;c. faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na.</hi> Long &amp;c. {repeat} Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="9" type="song">
                        <pb facs="tcp:173820:8"/>
                        <head>Of 5. IX. CANTVS.</head>
                        <byline>Richard Nicolson.</byline>
                        <p>
                           <gap reason="music">
                              <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                           </gap> SIng shepherds all, and in your roundelaies, and in: ij. your roundelaies, and in: ij. and in your rounde╌laies, Sing onely of faire <hi>Ori╌a╌naes</hi> praise, sing onely: ij. The gods aboue will help to beare a part, The gods aboue will help to beare a part, a part, will: ij. And men below, will trie their greatest art, And men below, will trie their grea╌test art, will: ij. Though neither gods nor men, can well apply, can well ap╌ply, though: ij. can well ap╌ply, Fit song or tune to praise her worthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, fit song or tune to praise her worthely, to praise her worthely. Then sang the shepherds, then sang the shepherds, then: ij. then sang the shepherds, and
<pb facs="tcp:173820:8"/>
                           <gap reason="music">
                              <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                           </gap> Nimphes of <hi>Diana,</hi> Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌ana,</hi> Long: ij. Long liue faire <hi>Ori╌ana,</hi> Long: ij. Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌ana,</hi> Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>a╌na.</hi> Then sang the shepherds, then: ij. then sang the shepherds, &amp; Nymphes of <hi>Di╌ana,</hi> of <hi>Dia╌na,</hi> Long liue faire <hi>Oria╌na,</hi> Long liue faire <hi>Oria╌na,</hi> Long: ij. Long liue faire <hi>Oria╌na.</hi> Long: ij. faire <hi>Ori╌a╌na.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="10" type="song">
                        <pb facs="tcp:173820:9"/>
                        <head>Of 5. X. CANTVS.</head>
                        <byline>Thomas Tomkins.</byline>
                        <p>
                           <gap reason="music">
                              <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                           </gap> THE Faunes &amp; Satirs trip╌ping, With liuely Nymphes, ij. {repeat} {repeat} {repeat} Of fresh coole brooks, coole brookes, {repeat} {repeat} &amp; fountaines, And those of woods and mountaines, Like Roes came nimbly skiping, came: ij. by signes their mirth vnriping, their: ij. ij. vnripping, My faire Queene, ij. They presen╌ted, With <hi>Amal╌the╌as</hi> twentie: ij. Brimfull of welthie plentie, And still to giue frequented, still to: ij. With bare gifts not contented, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented, not: ij. not: ij. not: ij. The demy gods pray to the gods supernall, supernall, the: ij. the: ij. Her life, Her wealth, Her
<pb facs="tcp:173820:9"/>
                           <gap reason="music">
                              <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                           </gap> fame, may be Eter╌nall. Her life, Her wealth, Her fame, may be Eternall, may: ij. ij. Then sang the shepherds and Nimphs of <hi>Di╌a╌na,</hi> ij. ij. Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na,</hi> faire <hi>Ori╌a╌na,</hi> faire: ij. Long: ij. Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="11" type="song">
                        <pb facs="tcp:173820:10"/>
                        <head>Of 5. XI. CANTVS:</head>
                        <byline>Michaell Cauendish.</byline>
                        <p>
                           <gap reason="music">
                              <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                           </gap> COme gentle swaines and shepherds dainty daughters, &amp; shepherds daintie daughters, Adornde, adornde, Come: ij. daintie daughters, ador╌ned, adornd with courtesie, {repeat} and comely duties, Come sing and ioy and grace with louely laughters, and grace with louely laugh╌ters, The birth day of the beauties, of beauties. Then sang the Shepherds and Nymphs of <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>a╌na,</hi> Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na,</hi> {repeat} Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na.</hi> faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na.</hi> Then sang the shepherds and Nymphs of <hi>Di╌a╌na,</hi> Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na.</hi> {repeat} faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na,</hi> faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="12" type="song">
                        <pb facs="tcp:173820:10"/>
                        <head>Of 5. XII. CANTVS.</head>
                        <byline>William Cobbold.</byline>
                        <p>
                           <gap reason="music">
                              <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                           </gap> WIthdraw your selues yee shepherds from your bowres, and strew the path with flowres, The Nimphs are comming, the &amp;c Sweetly the birds are chirping, The swift beasts run╌ning, the &amp;c. As all amazde they stand ij. still gazing, To see such bright stars blazing, bright stars blazing, loe Dian braue╌ly treading, The powres deuine to her doe vale their bonnets, their bonnets, Prepare your selues to sound your pasterall sonnets, Prepare your selues to sound, ij. your &amp;c. Then sang the shepherds &amp; Nymphs of Di╌a╌na, then &amp;c. Long liue faire O╌ri╌a╌na, faire O╌ri╌ana, Long &amp;c. ij. O╌ri╌a╌na, Long &amp;c. ij. ij, Long liue faire O╌ri╌a╌na.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="13" type="song">
                        <pb facs="tcp:173820:11"/>
                        <head>Of 5. XIII. CANTVS.</head>
                        <byline>Thomas Morley.</byline>
                        <p>
                           <gap reason="music">
                              <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                           </gap> ARise, awake, awake, awake you silly shepherds sleeping, awake, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wake you silly shepherds sleeping, Deuise, some honour for her sake to banish weeping, by mirth to banish weeping, Loe where she comes, Loe wher she comes, she comes in gaudie greene araying, in gaudie greene araying, araying, A Prince, of beauty rich and rare, for her delighting, Pretends to goe a Maying, You stately Nymphs draw neere, and strew your pathes with Ro╌ses, In you her trust re╌po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses, {repeat} Then sang the shepherds and Nimphs of <hi>Di╌a╌na,</hi> Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na,</hi> Long &amp;c. Long &amp;c. Then sang:</p>
                     </div>
                     <trailer>Heere endeth the songs of fiue parts.</trailer>
                  </div>
                  <div type="songs_of_six_parts">
                     <div n="14" type="song">
                        <pb facs="tcp:173820:11"/>
                        <head>Of 6. XIIII. CANTVS.</head>
                        <byline>Iohn Farmer.</byline>
                        <p>
                           <gap reason="music">
                              <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                           </gap> FAire Nymphs I heard one telling To beautifie the place, to &amp;c. The Faunes are running, are running, The shepherds their pipes tunening, {repeat} To shew their cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, The Lambs amazed leaue of their grasing, And blind their eies with gasing, Attended by the Muses, {repeat} and the Graces. Then sang the shepherds and Nimphs, the &amp;c. and Nymphs of <hi>Di╌a╌na,</hi> Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na,</hi> Long liue, Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na.</hi> {repeat}</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="15" type="song">
                        <pb facs="tcp:173820:12"/>
                        <head>Of 6. XV. CANTVS.</head>
                        <byline>Iohn Wilbye.</byline>
                        <p>
                           <gap reason="music">
                              <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                           </gap> THe Lady <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na,</hi> {repeat} Was dight all in the treasures all in the treasures of <hi>Guia╌na,</hi> Was dight, was dight, all &amp;c. And on her Grace a thousand, {repeat} Graces tended, And thus sang they, faire Queene of peace and plenty, The fairest Queene of twentie, Then with an Oliue wreath for peace re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>now╌ned, for peace renowned, Her virgin head they crowned, Which ceremony ended, ij. Which cere╌mony ended, ij. Vnto her Grace the thousand Graces bended. Then sang the shepherds &amp; Nymphs of Diana, Long liue faire Ori╌ana, ij. ij. ij. ij. ij. ij. Long liue faire O╌ri╌a╌na.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="16" type="song">
                        <pb facs="tcp:173820:12"/>
                        <head>Of 6. XVI. CANTVS.</head>
                        <byline>Thomas Hunt.</byline>
                        <p>
                           <gap reason="music">
                              <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                           </gap> HArk! hark! hark! hark! did yee euer heare, did &amp;c. so sweet, so sweet a sing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing? did ye &amp;c. They sing young loue to waken, ij. The Nymphs vnto the woods their Queene are bringing, their &amp;c. The &amp;c. their Queene are bring╌ing, There was a note well taken, there, there was &amp;c. there, there was &amp;c. O good! O most de╌uinely ditti'd, O most deuine, O most deuinely ditt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>'d, A Queene &amp; song most excellent, most excellently fitted, ij. most excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, ij. I neuer saw, I neuer saw a fairer, ij. I neuer heard a rarer, I neuer heard, ij. I neuer heard, I neuer heard a rarer. Then sung the Nymphs &amp; shepherds of Di╌a╌na. Long liue faire O╌ri╌a╌na, ij.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="17" type="song">
                        <pb facs="tcp:173820:13"/>
                        <head>Of 6. XVII. CANTVS.</head>
                        <byline>Thomas Weelkes.</byline>
                        <p>
                           <gap reason="music">
                              <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                           <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S <hi>Vesta</hi> was, from <hi>Latmos</hi> hill descending, from <hi>Latmos</hi> hill, from <hi>Latmos</hi> hill descen╌ding, She spied, she spied a maiden Queene, the same ascen╌ding, ascending, the same ascen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, the same ascen╌ding, Attended on by all the shepherds swain, {repeat} To whom <hi>Dianaes</hi> darlings, darlings, Came running down a maine, {repeat} {repeat} came running down amaine, {repeat} {repeat} amaine, First two by two, then three by three together, Leauing their Goddesse all alone hasted thether, And mingling with the shepherds of her traine, With mirthfull tunes, mirthfull tunes, her presence entertaine, {repeat}
<pb facs="tcp:173820:13"/>
                           <gap reason="music">
                              <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                           </gap> Then sang the shepherds and Nymphs of <hi>Di╌a╌na,</hi> Nymphs of <hi>Diana,</hi> Long liue faire <hi>Ori╌a╌na,</hi> faire <hi>Ori╌ana,</hi> Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na,</hi> {repeat} ij. <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na,</hi> Long liue faire <hi>Oriana,</hi> {repeat} faire <hi>Ori╌a╌na.</hi> {repeat} faire <hi>O╌riana.</hi> Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌ana,</hi> faire <hi>Ori╌a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na,</hi> {repeat} Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na.</hi> Long liue faire <hi>Ori╌a╌na.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="18" type="song">
                        <pb facs="tcp:173820:14"/>
                        <head>Of 6. XVIII. CANTVS.</head>
                        <byline>Iohn Milton.</byline>
                        <p>
                           <gap reason="music">
                              <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                           </gap> FAire <hi>Ori╌an,</hi> in the morne, before the day was borne, in ij. ij. With veluet steps on groūd, which made nor print nor soūd, Would see her Nymphs a bed, what liues those Ladies led, what: ij. what: ij. what: ij. what: ij. what: ij. those Ladies led, The Roses blushing sayd, O stay thou shepherds mayd, O stay: ij. And on a sodain all, they rose &amp; heard her call. Then sang those shepherds and Nymphs of <hi>Diana,</hi> then, ij. and Nymphs ij. of <hi>Dia╌na,</hi> Long liue faire <hi>Ori╌a╌na,</hi> Long: ij. Long: ij. faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="19" type="song">
                        <pb facs="tcp:173820:14"/>
                        <head>Of 6. XIX. CANTVS.</head>
                        <byline>Ellis Gibbons.</byline>
                        <p>
                           <gap reason="music">
                              <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                           </gap> ROund about her Charret with all admiring straines, ij. The <hi>Hya╌des</hi> and <hi>Drya╌des</hi> giue sweetest enter╌taynes, Lo how the gods ij. in re╌uells do accord, Whilst doth each goddesse melodies afford, whilst doth each goddesse melo╌dies afford: Now <hi>Baccus</hi> is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sorting, <hi>Siluanus</hi> fals a sporting, <hi>Amphions</hi> harp's reporting. To y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> shepherds pipes sing the Nymphs of <hi>Diana,</hi> Long liue faire <hi>O╌ria╌na.</hi> ij. ij. Long liue faire <hi>Ori╌ana,</hi> ij. faire <hi>Oria╌na.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="20" type="song">
                        <pb facs="tcp:173820:15"/>
                        <head>Of 6. XX. CANTVS.</head>
                        <byline>George Kyrbie.</byline>
                        <p>
                           <gap reason="music">
                              <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                           </gap> WIth Angels face &amp; brightnesse, &amp; o╌ri╌ent hew, faire <hi>O╌ria╌na,</hi> ij. faire <hi>Ori╌ana</hi> shining, With nimble foot she tript, with nimble foot she tripped, o're hills &amp; mountaines, o're: ij. At last in dale she rested, hard by <hi>Dianaes,</hi> fountaines ij. This is that maiden Queene of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Fairie land: With septer in her hand, ij. The Faunes &amp; Satirs dauncing, did shew their nimble lightnes, ij. &amp; brought their baskets full of herbs &amp; flowers. Then sang y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> shepherds &amp; Nymphs of <hi>Diana,</hi> Nymphs of <hi>Diana,</hi> Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌ana.</hi> ij. Long liue faire <hi>O╌riana.</hi> ij. ij. ij. faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="21" type="song">
                        <pb facs="tcp:173820:15"/>
                        <head>Of 6. XXI. CANTVS.</head>
                        <byline>Robert Iones.</byline>
                        <p>
                           <gap reason="music">
                              <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                           </gap> FAire <hi>O╌ria╌na</hi> ij. ij. seeming to winck at fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, Faire <hi>O╌ria╌na,</hi> seeming to winck at folly, Lay softly down to sleeping, to sleeping, Lay: ij. But hearing that the world was grown vnholly, her rest was turned to weeping, to: ij. to: ij. So wakt, shee sight, ij. and with crost armes, and: ij, sate drincking teares for others harmes, sate: ij. for others harmes. Then sang the Nymphs &amp; shepherds of <hi>Di╌a╌na,</hi> &amp;: ij. Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na,</hi> faire <hi>Ori╌ana.</hi> Long: ij. faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na,</hi> Long: ij. Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="22" type="song">
                        <pb facs="tcp:173820:16"/>
                        <head>Of 6. XXII. <hi>CANTVS.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <byline>Iohn Lisley.</byline>
                        <p>
                           <gap reason="music">
                              <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                           </gap> FAire <hi>Citharea</hi> presents her Doues, (sweet) <hi>Miner╌ua</hi> sin╌geth, <hi>Ioue</hi> giues a crowne, a garland <hi>Iuno</hi> bringeth, a garland: ij. <hi>Fame</hi> sūmōd each celestial power, <hi>Fame:</hi> ij. To bring their gifts to <hi>O╌ri╌anaes</hi> bower, to: ij. Then sang the shepherds and Nymphs of <hi>Dia╌na.</hi> Then ij. Long liue saire <hi>Ori╌ana</hi> Long: ij. Then sang the shepherds and Nymphs of <hi>Dia╌na,</hi> Then sang y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> shepherds &amp; Nymphs of <hi>Dia╌na,</hi> Long liue faire <hi>Ori╌ana.</hi> Long: ij. ij. Long: ij. Long: ij. Long liue faire O ri a╌na. ij.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="23" type="song">
                        <pb facs="tcp:173820:16"/>
                        <head>Of 6. XXIII. <hi>CANTVS.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <byline>Thomas Morley.</byline>
                        <p>
                           <gap reason="music">
                              <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                           </gap> HArd by a Cristal foun╌taine, ij. <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na</hi> the bright, ij. lay downe a sleeping, lay &amp;c. The birds they finely cherped, ij. The birds they sinely cherped, ij. The windes were stilled, Sweetly with these accenting, The aire was filled, This is that faire whose head a crowne deserueth, Which heauen for her re╌serueth, ij. Leaue shepherds your Lambs keepeing, ij. Vpon the barren mountaines, ij. the &amp;c. And Mymphs at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend on her and leaue your bowres, For she the shepherds life maintaines and youres. Then sang the shepherds &amp; Nimphs, Nimphs of Di╌ana, ij, Long: ij.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="24" type="song">
                        <pb facs="tcp:173820:17"/>
                        <head>Of 6 XXIIII. CANTVS.</head>
                        <byline>Edward Iohnson.</byline>
                        <p>
                           <gap reason="music">
                              <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                           </gap> COme come blessed Bird and with thy sugred rel╌lish, Help our declining quire now to embellish, For Bonny bootes, for Bonny bootes that so a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loft would fetch it, that &amp;c. Oh he is dead, and none of vs can reach it, and none of vs can reach it, Then tune to vs sweet Bird thy shrill recor╌der, for fault of better will serue in the <hi>Corus,</hi> Begin and we will follow thee in order, in order, in order, Then sang the Woodborne minstrell of <hi>Diana,</hi> Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na.</hi> ij, Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na.</hi> Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:173820:17"/>
                  <p>ALTVS.</p>
                  <p>MADRIGALES The Triumphes of Oriana, to 5. and 6. voices: com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posed by diuers seuerall <hi>aucthors.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Newly published by Thomas Morley Batcheler of Musick, and one of the gentlemen of her</hi> Maiesties honorable Chappell.</p>
                  <p>1601.</p>
                  <p>IN LONDON PRINTED BY THOMAS ESTE, the assigne of Thomas Morley.</p>
                  <p>¶ Cum priuilegio Regiae Maiestatis.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="table_of_contents">
                  <pb facs="tcp:173820:18"/>
                  <head>¶ The Table of all the Madrigales contained in these bookes, vvith the names of their seuerall authors.</head>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Songs of 5. parts.</head>
                     <list>
                        <item>Hence Stars you dazell but the sight. <hi>Michaell Este.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>VVIth Angells face and brightnesse. I <hi>Daniell Norcome.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Lightly she whipped o're y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> dales. II <hi>Iohn Mundy Batcheler of Musick</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Long liue faire <hi>Oriana.</hi> III <hi>Ellis Gibbons.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>All creatures now are merry. IIII <hi>Iohn Benet.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Faire <hi>Oriana</hi> beauties Queene. V <hi>Iohn Hilton. Batcheler of Musick</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>The Nymphs and shepherds danced. VI <hi>George Marson. Batch. of Musick</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Calme was the Aire. VII <hi>Richard Carlton. Batch. of Musick</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Thus bonny bootes the birth day. VIII <hi>Iohn Holmes.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Sing shepherds all. IX <hi>Richard Nicolson.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>The Faunes and Satirs tripping. X <hi>Thomas Tomkins.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Come gentle swaines. XI <hi>Michaell Cauendish.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Withdraw your selues yee shepherds. XII <hi>William Cobbold.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Arise awake you silly shepherds sleping. XIII <hi>Thomas Morley Batch. of Musick</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Song of 6. parts.</head>
                     <list>
                        <item>Faire Nymphes I heard one telling. XIIII <hi>Iohn Farmer.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>The lady <hi>Oriana.</hi> XV <hi>Iohn Wilby.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Hark! hark, did you euer heare &amp;c. XVI <hi>Thomas Hunt. Batch. of Musick</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>As <hi>Ʋesta</hi> was from <hi>Latmos</hi> hill &amp;c. XVII <hi>Thomas Weelks.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Faire <hi>Orian</hi> in the morne. XVIII <hi>Iohn Milton.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Round about her Charret &amp;c. XIX <hi>Ellis Gibbons.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>With Angells face and brightnesse. XX <hi>George Kirbye.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Faire <hi>Oriana</hi> seeming to wink at folly. XXI <hi>Robert Iones.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Faire <hi>Citharea</hi> presents her Doues &amp;c. XXII <hi>Iohn Lisley.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Hard by a Christall fountaine. XXIII <hi>Thomas Morley. Batch. of Musick</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Come blessed Byrd &amp;c. XXIIII <hi>Edward Iohnson. Batch. of Musick</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
               <div type="dedication">
                  <pb facs="tcp:173820:18"/>
                  <head>TO THE RIGHT HO<seg rend="sup">norable</seg>. THE LORD Charles Howard <hi>Earle of Notingham, Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron</hi> of <hi>Effingham,</hi> Knight of the Noble order of the <hi>Garter,</hi> Lord high <hi>Admirall</hi> of <hi>England, Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and <hi>Wales, &amp;c.</hi> And one of her Majesties most honorable Priuie Counsell.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>RIGHT HO<seg rend="sup">norable</seg>.</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Haue aduentured to dedicate these few discordant tunes to be censured by the ingenious disposition of your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ships Honorable rare perfection, perswading my selfe, that these labours, composed by me and others, (as in the sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uey hereof, your Lordship may well perceiue) may not by any meanes passe, without the malignitie of some maliti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous <hi>Momus,</hi> whose malice (being as toothsome as the <hi>Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders</hi> sting) couched in the progres of a wayfayring mans passage, might make him retire though almost at his iourneyes end. Two speci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all <hi>Motiues</hi> haue imbouldened me (right Honorable) in this my proceeding. First, for that I consider, that as the body cannot bee without the shadow: so <hi>Homer</hi> (the Prince of Poets) may not be without a <hi>Zoilist:</hi> The second &amp; last is (the most forcible motiue) I know, (not onely by report, but also by experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment) your Lordship, to bee not onely <hi>Philomusus</hi> a louer of the <hi>Muses,</hi> and of learning: but <hi>Philomathes,</hi> a personage alway desirous, (though in all Arts sufficiently skilfull) to come to a more high perfection or <hi>Summum bonum.</hi> I will not trouble your Lordship with to to tedious circumstances, onely I humbly intreat your Lordship (in the name of many) to patronage this work with no lesse acceptance, then I with a willing and kinde hart dedicate it. So shall I think the <hi>initium</hi> of this worke not onely happely begun, but to bee <hi>finited</hi> with a more happie period.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Your Honours deuoted in all dutie, Thomas Morley.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div n="altus" type="musical_part">
                  <div type="songs_of_five_parts">
                     <div type="song">
                        <pb facs="tcp:173820:19"/>
                        <head>Of 5. ALTVS.</head>
                        <byline>Michaell Este.</byline>
                        <p>
                           <gap reason="music">
                              <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                           </gap> HEnce Stars, ij. to dim of light, you dazel but the sight, you teach to grope by night, to ij. you teach to grope by night, you: ij. you teach to grope by night, to ij. See heere the shepherds sttar, excelling you so far, Then <hi>Phebus</hi> wipt his eyes, wipt ij. then ij. wipt his eies, &amp; <hi>Zephirus</hi> cleer'd the Skies, in sweet accented cries, in ij. Then sang the shepherds &amp; Nymphs of <hi>Diana,</hi> Nymphs: ij. Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌ana,</hi> faire ij. Long: ij. faire ij. Long: ij. Long: ij.</p>
                        <p>This song being sent to late, and all the other printed, I plast it before the rest, rather then to leaue it out.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="1" type="song">
                        <pb facs="tcp:173820:19"/>
                        <head>Of 5. I. ALTVS.</head>
                        <byline>Daniell Norcome.</byline>
                        <p>
                           <gap reason="music">
                              <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                           </gap> WIth Angels face and brightnesse, ij. &amp; orient hew, faire <hi>Ori╌a╌na</hi> shi╌ning, with nimble foote she tripped, ij. o're hils, o're hills &amp; mountaines, hills &amp; moūtaines, &amp; mountaines, at last in dale she rested: hard by <hi>Di╌a╌nas</hi> fountaines: this is y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> maiden <hi>Queene,</hi> ij. of the Fayrie land, with scepter in her hand, ij. the Faunes and Satires dauncing, did shew their nimble nimble lightnes, Faire <hi>Nais</hi> and the Nimphs did leaue their bowers, &amp; brought their baskets full of hearbs &amp; flowres. Thē sang the shepherds &amp; Nimphs of <hi>Di╌a╌na,</hi> ij. Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na.</hi> ij. ij. ii. ij.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="2" type="song">
                        <pb facs="tcp:173820:20"/>
                        <head>Of 5. II. ALTVS.</head>
                        <byline>Iohn Mundy.</byline>
                        <p>
                           <gap reason="music">
                              <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                           <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>Ightly she whipped o're y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> dales, ij. ij. making y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> woods proud with her presēce, with her presence, making: ij. gently she trode the flowres, she trode y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> flowres, ij. &amp; they as gētly kist her tender feet, y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> birds in their best language bad her welcome, ij. being proud that <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na</hi> heard their song: the cloue foot Satires singing, made Musick to the Faunes a daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing, &amp; both to gether with an emphasis, sang <hi>O╌ri╌a╌nas</hi> praises, ij. ij. whilst the aioyning woods with melody, with melody, did entertain their sweet, ij. their sweet sweet harmony,
<pb facs="tcp:173820:20"/>
                           <gap reason="music">
                              <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                           </gap> Then sang the sheperds and Nimphes of <hi>Di╌a╌na,</hi> of <hi>Dia╌na,</hi> ij. of <hi>Di╌a╌na,</hi> of <hi>Di╌a╌na,</hi> Long liue faire <hi>Ori╌a╌na,</hi> faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na,</hi> ij. <hi>Ori╌a╌na,</hi> ij. ij. ij. ij. ij. faire <hi>Ori╌a╌na.</hi> ij.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="3" type="song">
                        <pb facs="tcp:173820:21"/>
                        <head>Of 5. III. ALTVS.</head>
                        <byline>Ellis Gibbons.</byline>
                        <p>
                           <gap reason="music">
                              <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                           </gap> LOng liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na,</hi> Heark, did you euer heare so sweet a sing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, They sing young Loue, young Loue, The Nimphs vnto the woods, ij. ij. their Queene are bring╌ing, Ther was a note wel taken, O, good, Hark, how ioyful╌ly, ij. how ioyfully, ij. tis ditti'd, how ioyfully, ij. ij. tis dit╌ti'd, A Queene &amp; Song most excellently fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, I ne╌uer heard a rarer, I ne╌uer saw a fairer, I ne╌uer heard a rarer. Then sing ye Shepherds and Nimphes of <hi>Di╌a╌na,</hi> Nimphs &amp;c. Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na,</hi> ij. Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na,</hi> ij. Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na,</hi> faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="4" type="song">
                        <pb facs="tcp:173820:21"/>
                        <head>Of 5. IIII. ALTVS.</head>
                        <byline>Iohn Benet.</byline>
                        <p>
                           <gap reason="music">
                              <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                           </gap> ALL cre'tures now are merry merry minded, merry merry minded, {repeat} {repeat} The shepherds daughters playing, {repeat} are playing, are playing, The Nimphes are Fa la laing, {repeat} Fa la la la laing, Fa la la la la la laing, Yond bugle was well winded, At <hi>Orianaes</hi> presence each thing smileth, the flowers themselues discouer, {repeat} Birds ouer hir do ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, Musicke the time beguileth {repeat} See wher she comes, {repeat} with flowry garlands crowned, Queene of all queenes renowned. {repeat} Then sang the shepherds &amp; Nimphes of <hi>Diana,</hi> Nimphes of <hi>Diana,</hi> long liue faire <hi>Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>a╌na,</hi> Long liue, Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na,</hi> faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na,</hi> faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="5" type="song">
                        <pb facs="tcp:173820:22"/>
                        <head>Of 5. V. ALTVS.</head>
                        <byline>Iohn Hilton.</byline>
                        <p>
                           <gap reason="music">
                              <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                           </gap> FAire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na</hi> beauties Queene, faire <hi>Ori╌a╌na,</hi> {repeat} faire <hi>O╌ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>a╌na</hi> beauties Queene, Tripped a long the verdant greene, tripped along the greene, tripped along the verdant greene, The Faunes and Satires, {repeat} came running running out, Skipped and danced {repeat} {repeat} round about, {repeat} Flora forsooke hir bowrs, Flora forsooke hir painted bowres, And made a Coronet of flowres, of flowers, and &amp;c. Then sang the Nimphs of chast <hi>Di╌a╌na,</hi> of chast <hi>Di╌a╌na,</hi> Long Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na,</hi> Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na,</hi> {repeat} faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na,</hi> {repeat} faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="6" type="song">
                        <pb facs="tcp:173820:22"/>
                        <head>Of 5. VI. ALTVS.</head>
                        <byline>George Marson.</byline>
                        <p>
                           <gap reason="music">
                              <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                           </gap> THe Nimphs and shepheards daunced, Lauoltos in a da╌zy tapstred vally, Loue loue loue from their face lamps glaunced, Till wantonly they dally, Then in a Rose bankt ally, Bright Maiestie ad╌uanced, {repeat} A crowne grac't Virgin whom all people honor, {repeat} all &amp;c. They leaue their sport a╌mazed, Runne all to looke, all to looke vpon hir, A moment scarce they ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed, Ere beauties splendor all their eies had dazed, desire to see yet euer fixed on hir. Then sang the Shepherds &amp; Nimphs of <hi>Di╌ana,</hi> Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌ana.</hi> {repeat} liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na. O╌ri╌a╌na,</hi> liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na.</hi> liue, &amp;c. liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na,</hi> faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="7" type="song">
                        <pb facs="tcp:173820:23"/>
                        <head>Of 5. VII. ALTVS.</head>
                        <byline>Richard Carlton.</byline>
                        <p>
                           <gap reason="music">
                              <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                           </gap> CAlme was the aire, and cleere the skye, Faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na</hi> passing by, passing by, Ouer the downes to I╌da plains ij. I╌da plains, Wher heau'n born sisters with their traines, Did all attend hir sacred beauty, Striuing to excell in duty, to ex: ij. Satirs and Nimphs daun╌cing together, daun: ij ij. Shepherds triumphing triumphing flocking thether, Seeing their louely mistris ther, their &amp;c. That kept their flocks &amp; them from feare, That kept: &amp;c. With hie strayn'd voice, &amp; harts reioyce, re╌ioyce. Thus sang the sheperds and Nimphs of <hi>Dia╌na,</hi> Long liue faire <hi>O╌ria╌na,</hi> ij. ij Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na.</hi> faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na.</hi> ij</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="8" type="song">
                        <pb facs="tcp:173820:23"/>
                        <head>Of 5. VIII. ALTVS.</head>
                        <byline>Iohn Holmes.</byline>
                        <p>
                           <gap reason="music">
                              <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                           </gap> THus bonny boots y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> birth day cele╌bra╌ted, the &amp;c. ce╌lebra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, Of her his Lady deerest, Lady deerest, Faire <hi>O╌ria╌na,</hi> which to his hart was neerest, The Nymphs &amp; shepherds feasted, ij. With clowted creame were, with clowted creame, with clowted creame were, and to sing were request<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, re╌quested, Loe heere the faire created (Quoth he) the worlds chiefe goddesse, Sing then, the &amp;c. for she is Bonny bootes sweet Mistres. Then sang the shepherds &amp; Nymphs of <hi>Di╌a╌na,</hi> Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na. O╌ri╌a╌na,</hi> faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na.</hi> Long: &amp;c. ij. ij. ij. faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na.</hi> Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na. O╌ri╌a╌na.</hi> ij.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="9" type="song">
                        <pb facs="tcp:173820:24"/>
                        <head>Of 5. IX. ALTVS.</head>
                        <byline>Richard Nicolson.</byline>
                        <p>
                           <gap reason="music">
                              <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                           </gap> SIng shepherds all, and in your roundelaies, and in: ij. your roundelaies, and in your roundelaies, and in your rounde╌laies, Sing onely of faire <hi>Ori╌a╌naes</hi> praise, faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌naes</hi> praise, sing onely: ij. faire <hi>Oria╌naes</hi> praise: The gods aboue will help to beare a part, will help to beare a part, the gods: ij. will help to beare a part, And men below will trie their grea╌test art, And men below, will trie their greatest art, will: ij. Though neither gods nor men, Though neither gods nor men can well apply, though: ij. can well apply, can: ij. Fit song or tune to praise her worthely, to praise: ij. fit song or tune to praise her worthely. to praise: ij.
<pb facs="tcp:173820:24"/>
                           <gap reason="music">
                              <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                           </gap> to praise her worthely. Then sang the shepherds, thē sang: ij. thē sang the shepherds, then: ij. and Nimphes of <hi>Di╌a╌na,</hi> of <hi>Di╌ana,</hi> Long liue faire <hi>Ori╌a na,</hi> Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌ana,</hi> Long: ij. Long: ij. Long liue faire <hi>O╌ria╌na,</hi> faire <hi>O╌ria╌na.</hi> Then sang the shepherds, then sang the shepheards, thē: ij. the shepherds, &amp; Nymphes of <hi>Diana,</hi> of <hi>Di╌a╌na,</hi> Lōg liue faire <hi>O╌riana.</hi> faire <hi>Ori╌ana.</hi> Long liue faire <hi>Oria╌na.</hi> Long: ij. Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na.</hi> faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="10" type="song">
                        <pb facs="tcp:173820:25"/>
                        <head>Of 5. X. ALTVS.</head>
                        <byline>Thomas Tomkins.</byline>
                        <p>
                           <gap reason="music">
                              <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                           </gap> THE Faunes &amp; Satirs, trip╌ping, With liuely Nymphs, ij. ij. liuely Nymphs, with liuely Nymphs, Of fresh coole brooks, coole: ij. of: ij. &amp; fountaines, And those of woods and mountaines, and: ij. Like Roes came nimbly skiping, came: ij. their mirth vnriping, their: ij. vn: ij. their: ij. vnrip╌ping, My faire Queene, ij. They presen╌ted, In peaces armes <hi>Amaltheas</hi> twēty, <hi>Amal╌the╌as</hi> twentie: Brim full of welthie plentie, And still to giue frequented, And: ij. With bare gifts not contented, not: ij. With gifts: ij. The demy gods pray to the gods supernall, pray: ij. supernall, Her life, Her wealth,
<pb facs="tcp:173820:25"/>
                           <gap reason="music">
                              <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                           </gap> Her fame, may be Eter╌nall. Her life, her life, Her wealth, Her fame, may: ij. Her life: ij. may be Eter╌nall, ij. Eternall, Then sang the shepherds and Nimphs of <hi>Di╌a╌na,</hi> and: ij. of: ij and: ij. Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌ana.</hi> faire <hi>Ori╌a╌na</hi> faire: ij. faire: ij. Long: ij. faire: ij. Long: ij. faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="11" type="song">
                        <pb facs="tcp:173820:26"/>
                        <head>Of 5. XI. ALTVS.</head>
                        <byline>Michaell Cauendish.</byline>
                        <p>
                           <gap reason="music">
                              <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                           </gap> COme gentle swaines and shepherds dainty daughters, Adornd with courtesie and comely duties, Come &amp;c. comely du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, adornd with courtesie and comely duties, and comely duties, and &amp;c. Come sing and ioy and grace with loue, and grace with louely laugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, The birth day of the beauties, of beauties. Then sang the Shepherds, Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na,</hi> {repeat} {repeat} Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na.</hi> Then sang the shepherds, Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na.</hi> {repeat} Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na,</hi> Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="12" type="song">
                        <pb facs="tcp:173820:26"/>
                        <head>Of 5. XII. ALTVS.</head>
                        <byline>William Cobbold.</byline>
                        <p>
                           <gap reason="music">
                              <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                           </gap> WIth wreathes of Rose and lawrell, withdraw your selues yee shepherds from your bowres, and strew the path with flowres, ij. The Nimphs are comming, are comming, Sweetly the birds are chirping, The swift beasts run╌ning, ij. As all amazde they stand still gazing, To see such bright stars blazing, lo Dian brauely tread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, her dainty daughter leading, leading, The powres deuine, the &amp;c. to her doe vale their bonnets, Prepare your selues to sound your pasterall son╌nets, ij. your pasterall sonnets. Then sang the shepherds &amp; Nymphs of Di╌ana, ij. Long liue faire Ori╌a╌na, ij. O╌ri╌ana, Long &amp;c. Long liue faire O╌ri╌a╌na. ij. ij, ij.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="13" type="song">
                        <pb facs="tcp:173820:27"/>
                        <head>Of 5. XIII. ALTVS.</head>
                        <byline>Thomas Morley.</byline>
                        <p>
                           <gap reason="music">
                              <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                           </gap> ARise, awake, awake you silly sheperds sleeping, awake, awake, awake you silly shepherds slee╌ping, Deuise, deuise some honour for her sake to banish weeping, by mirth to banish wee╌ping, she comes loe wher, Loe where she comes in gaudie greene a╌ray╌ing, loe wher she comes, she comes in gaudie greene aray╌ing, A Prince, {repeat} of beauty rich and rare, for her delight╌ing, Pretends to goe a May<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, In you her trust reposes, {repeat} re╌poses. Sing then ye shepherds and Nimphs of <hi>Di╌a╌na,</hi> Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na,</hi> {repeat} Long liue, Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na.</hi> Sing then:</p>
                     </div>
                     <trailer>Heere endeth the songs of fiue parts.</trailer>
                  </div>
                  <div type="songs_of_six_parts">
                     <div n="14" type="song">
                        <pb facs="tcp:173820:27"/>
                        <head>Of 6. XIIII. ALTVS.</head>
                        <byline>Iohn Farmer.</byline>
                        <p>
                           <gap reason="music">
                              <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                           </gap> FAire Nymphs I heard one telling, <hi>Di╌a╌naes</hi> traine is hunting, in this chace, To beauti╌fie the place, The Faunes are rūning, are rūning, The &amp;c. The shepherds their pipes tuneing, the &amp;c. The Lambs ama╌zed leaue of their grasing, And blind their eies with ga╌sing, Whilst the earths goddesse doth draw neere your places, Attended by the Muse, {repeat} Attended by the Muses and the Graces, the Gra╌ces. Then sang the shepherds &amp; Nimphs, &amp; Nymphs Then &amp;c. the shepherds &amp; Nymphs of <hi>Di╌a╌na,</hi> Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na,</hi> ij. Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na.</hi> {repeat} <hi>O╌ria╌na.</hi> Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="15" type="song">
                        <pb facs="tcp:173820:28"/>
                        <head>Of 6. XV. ALTVS.</head>
                        <byline>Iohn Wilbye.</byline>
                        <p>
                           <gap reason="music">
                              <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                           </gap> THe Lady <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na,</hi> {repeat} Was dight all in the treasures of <hi>Guiana,</hi> Was &amp;c. And on her Grace a thousand Graces tended, a thousand graces tended, And thus sang they, faire Queene of peace &amp; plenty, The fairest Queene of twentie, Then with an Oliue wreath for peace renowned, Her Virgin head they crowned, they crowned; Which ceremony ended, {repeat} Which ceremo╌ny ended, Vnto her Grace the thousand Graces bended. Then sang the shepherds &amp; Nymphs of <hi>Di╌a╌na,</hi> Long liue faire <hi>Ori╌ana.</hi> {repeat} Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na,</hi> faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na,</hi> faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na.</hi> Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="16" type="song">
                        <pb facs="tcp:173820:28"/>
                        <head>Of 6. XVI. ALTVS.</head>
                        <byline>Thomas Hunt.</byline>
                        <p>
                           <gap reason="music">
                              <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                           </gap> HArk! hark! hark! ij. did yee euer heare so sweet, so sweet a singing? did ye euer heare, ij. so sweet, so sweet a singing? They sing young loue to waken, to waken, ij. The Nymphs vnto the woods, vnto the woods, ij. their Queene are bringing, There was a note well taken, ij. there &amp;c. well taken, Hark! hark! hark! hark! O good! O most deuinely ditti'd, ij. A Queene &amp; song, most excellently fitted, most ex╌cellent╌ly, most excellently fitted, I neuer saw a fayrer, ij. I &amp;c. a fairer, I neuer heard a rarer, ij. ij. a rarer. Then sung the Nymphs &amp; shepherds of Di╌a╌na. Long liue faire O╌ri╌ana, ij. ij. ij. faire Oria╌na. ij.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="17" type="song">
                        <pb facs="tcp:173820:29"/>
                        <head>Of 6. XVII. ALTVS.</head>
                        <byline>Thomas Weelkes.</byline>
                        <p>
                           <gap reason="music">
                              <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                           <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S <hi>Vesta</hi> was descen╌ding, from <hi>Latmos</hi> hill des<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cen╌ding, She spied a maiden Queene the same ascen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, ascending, the same ascen╌ding, ascending, the same ascen╌ding, Attended on by all the shepherds swain, ij. To whom <hi>Dianaes</hi> darlings, ij. Came running down a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine, ij. ij. Came running downe a╌maine, ij. First two by two, and three by three to╌ge╌ther, Leauing their God╌desse, hasted thether, And mingling with the shepheards of her traine, of her traine, With mirthfull tunes, ij. her presence entertaine, her presence
<pb facs="tcp:173820:29"/>
                           <gap reason="music">
                              <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                           </gap> entertaine, Then sang the shepherds and Nymphs of <hi>Diana,</hi> Nymphs of <hi>Dia╌na,</hi> of <hi>Di╌a╌na,</hi> Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na,</hi> Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na,</hi> {repeat} faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na,</hi> Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌ana,</hi> {repeat} {repeat} faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na,</hi> Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na, O╌ri╌a╌na,</hi> {repeat} faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="18" type="song">
                        <pb facs="tcp:173820:30"/>
                        <head>Of 6. XVIII. ALTVS.</head>
                        <byline>Iohn Milton.</byline>
                        <p>
                           <gap reason="music">
                              <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                           </gap> FAire <hi>O╌ri╌an,</hi> in the morne, before the day was borne, in the morne, in the morne, before the day was borne, With veluet steps on ground, which made nor print nor sound, Would see her Nymphs a bed, what liues those Ladies led, those: ij. those: ij. those: ij. what: ij. those: ij. what: ij. those ij The Roses blushing sayd, O stay thou shepherds mayd, O stay: ij. And on a sodain all, they rose &amp; heard her call. Then sang those shepherds and Nymphs of <hi>Diana,</hi> then ij. of <hi>Di╌ana,</hi> Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na,</hi> Long: ij. Long: ij. faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="19" type="song">
                        <pb facs="tcp:173820:30"/>
                        <head>Of 6. XIX. ALTVS.</head>
                        <byline>Ellis Gibbons.</byline>
                        <p>
                           <gap reason="music">
                              <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                           </gap> ROund about her Charret with all admiring strains, The <hi>Hya╌des</hi> and <hi>Drya╌des</hi> giue sweetest entertaynes, Lo how the gods in reuells do ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord, Whilst doth each goddesse melodies afford, ij. whilst doth each goddesse melodies afford, afford, Now <hi>Baccus</hi> is consorting, <hi>Amphions</hi> harp's reporting. To y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> shepherds pipes sing the Nymphs of <hi>Diana,</hi> Long liue faire <hi>Oria╌na.</hi> Long: ij. Long: ij. Long liue faire <hi>Ori╌ana.</hi> ij.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="20" type="song">
                        <pb facs="tcp:173820:31"/>
                        <head>Of 6. XX. ALTVS.</head>
                        <byline>George Kyrbie.</byline>
                        <p>
                           <gap reason="music">
                              <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                           </gap> WIth Angels face &amp; brightnesse, &amp; o╌ri╌ent hew, faire <hi>Oria╌na,</hi> ij. faire <hi>Ori╌ana</hi> shining, O're hills &amp; mountaines, o're: ij. and mountaines, At last in dale she rested, hard by <hi>Dianaes</hi> fountaines, <hi>Dianaes</hi> foūtaines, With septer in her hand, ij. The Faunes &amp; Satirs dauncing, ij. did shew their nimble lightnes, Faire <hi>Nais</hi> and the Nymphes did leaue their bowers, Then sang the shepherds &amp; Nymphs of <hi>Diana,</hi> Nymphs of <hi>Diana,</hi> Long liue faire <hi>Ori╌a╌na,</hi> faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na.</hi> ij. Long liue, Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌ana.</hi> Long: ij. Long: ij.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="21" type="song">
                        <pb facs="tcp:173820:31"/>
                        <head>Of 6. XXI. ALTVS.</head>
                        <byline>Robert Iones.</byline>
                        <p>
                           <gap reason="music">
                              <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                           </gap> FAire <hi>O╌ria╌na</hi> ij. ij. seeming to winck at folly, ij. at folly, Lay softly down, lay softly down a slee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping, a sleeping, lay: ij. But hearing that the world was grown vnholly, but: ij. Her rest was turnd to weeping, ij. ij. So wakt, so wakt, shee sight, ij. ij. &amp; with crost armes, sate drincking teares for others harms. ij. for ij. Then sang the Nymphs &amp; shepherds of <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>a╌na,</hi> &amp;: ij. Long liue faire <hi>Oria╌na,</hi> faire <hi>Ori╌ana.</hi> ij. faire: ij faire: ij. Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌ana.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="22" type="song">
                        <pb facs="tcp:173820:32"/>
                        <head>Of 6. XXII. <hi>ALTVS.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <byline>Iohn Lisley.</byline>
                        <p>
                           <gap reason="music">
                              <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                           </gap> FAire <hi>Citharea</hi> presents her Doues, presents ij. <hi>Miner╌ua</hi> singeth, sing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth, <hi>Ioue</hi> giues a crowne, a garland <hi>Iuno</hi> bringeth, a garland: ij. <hi>Fame</hi> sūmōd each celestial power, celest: ij. <hi>Fame:</hi> ij. To bring their gifts to <hi>Ori╌anaes</hi> bower, to: ij. Then sang the shepherds &amp; Nymphs of <hi>Dia╌na,</hi> Then ij. Long liue faire <hi>Ori╌ana,</hi> Then sang the shepherds and Nymphs of <hi>Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na.</hi> Then: ij. Long liue faire <hi>Ori╌ana.</hi> ¶ O╌ria╌na. fair Ori╌a╌na. ij. ij. ij. faire Ori╌a╌na, Long &amp;c. Long &amp;c. faire O╌ri╌a╌na.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="23" type="song">
                        <pb facs="tcp:173820:32"/>
                        <head>Of 6. XXIII. <hi>ALTVS.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <byline>Thomas Morley.</byline>
                        <p>
                           <gap reason="music">
                              <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                           </gap> HArd by a Cri╌stall foun╌taine, ij. <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na</hi> the bright lay downe a slee╌ping, lay &amp;c. The birds they finely cherped, ij. The birds they finely cherped, ij. ij. The windes were stil╌led, Sweetly with these accen╌ting, ij. The aire was fil╌led, This is that faire whose head a crowne deserueth, Which heauen for her reserueth, reser╌ueth, ij. Leaue shepherds your Lambs keepeing, ij. Vpon the barren moun╌taine, ij. ij. And Mymphs attend on her and leaue your bowres, For she the shepherds life maintaines and youres. Then sang the shepherds &amp; Nimphs, Nimphs of Di╌ana, ij. Long liue faire ¶</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="24" type="song">
                        <pb facs="tcp:173820:33"/>
                        <head>Of 6 XXIIII. ALTVS.</head>
                        <byline>Edward Iohnson.</byline>
                        <p>
                           <gap reason="music">
                              <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                           </gap> COme blessed: For Bonny bootes that so a loft would fetch it, that so a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loft would fetch it, that so aloft would fetch it, Oh he is dead, he is dead, and none of vs can reach it, Then tune to vs sweet Bird thy shrill recorder, <hi>Elpin,</hi> and I and <hi>Do╌rus,</hi> for fault of better will serue in the <hi>Corus,</hi> Begin and we will follow thee in or╌der. Then sang the Woodborne minstrell of <hi>Diana,</hi> Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na.</hi> Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na.</hi> faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na.</hi> Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:173820:33"/>
                  <p>TENOR.</p>
                  <p>MADRIGALES The Triumphes of Oriana, to 5. and 6. voices: com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posed by diuers seuerall <hi>aucthors.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Newly published by Thomas Morley Batcheler of Musick, and one of the gentlemen of her</hi> Maiesties honorable Chappell.</p>
                  <p>1601.</p>
                  <p>IN LONDON PRINTED BY THOMAS ESTE, the assigne of Thomas Morley.</p>
                  <p>¶ Cum priuilegio Regiae Maiestatis.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="table_of_contents">
                  <pb facs="tcp:173820:34"/>
                  <head>¶ The Table of all the Madrigales contained in these bookes, vvith the names of their seuerall authors.</head>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Songs of 5. parts.</head>
                     <list>
                        <item>Hence Stars you dazell but the sight. <hi>Michaell Este.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>VVIth Angells face and brightnesse. I <hi>Daniell Norcome.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Lightly she whipped o're y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> dales. II <hi>Iohn Mundy Batcheler of Musick</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Long liue faire <hi>Oriana.</hi> III <hi>Ellis Gibbons.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>All creatures now are merry. IIII <hi>Iohn Benet.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Faire <hi>Oriana</hi> beauties Queene. V <hi>Iohn Hilton. Batcheler of Musick</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>The Nymphs and shepherds danced. VI <hi>George Marson. Batch. of Musick</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Calme was the Aire. VII <hi>Richard Carlton. Batch. of Musick</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Thus bonny bootes the birth day. VIII <hi>Iohn Holmes.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Sing shepherds all. IX <hi>Richard Nicolson.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>The Faunes and Satirs tripping. X <hi>Thomas Tomkins.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Come gentle swaines. XI <hi>Michaell Cauendish.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Withdraw your selues yee shepherds. XII <hi>William Cobbold.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Arise awake you silly shepherds sleping. XIII <hi>Thomas Morley Batch. of Musick</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Song of 6. parts.</head>
                     <list>
                        <item>Faire Nymphes I heard one telling. XIIII <hi>Iohn Farmer.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>The lady <hi>Oriana.</hi> XV <hi>Iohn Wilby.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Hark! hark, did you euer heare &amp;c. XVI <hi>Thomas Hunt. Batch. of Musick</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>As <hi>Ʋesta</hi> was from <hi>Latmos</hi> hill &amp;c. XVII <hi>Thomas Weelks.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Faire <hi>Orian</hi> in the morne. XVIII <hi>Iohn Milton.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Round about her Charret &amp;c. XIX <hi>Ellis Gibbons.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>With Angells face and brightnesse. XX <hi>George Kirbye.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Faire <hi>Oriana</hi> seeming to wink at folly. XXI <hi>Robert Iones.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Faire <hi>Citharea</hi> presents her Doues &amp;c. XXII <hi>Iohn Lisley.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Hard by a Christall fountaine. XXIII <hi>Thomas Morley. Batch. of Musick</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Come blessed Byrd &amp;c. XXIIII <hi>Edward Iohnson. Batch. of Musick</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
               <div type="dedication">
                  <pb facs="tcp:173820:34"/>
                  <head>TO THE RIGHT HO<seg rend="sup">norable</seg>. THE LORD Charles Howard <hi>Earle of Notingham, Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron</hi> of <hi>Effingham,</hi> Knight of the Noble order of the <hi>Garter,</hi> Lord high <hi>Admirall</hi> of <hi>England, Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and <hi>Wales, &amp;c.</hi> And one of her Majesties most honorable Priuie Counsell.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>RIGHT HO<seg rend="sup">norable</seg>.</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Haue aduentured to dedicate these few discordant tunes to be censured by the ingenious disposition of your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ships Honorable rare perfection, perswading my selfe, that these labours, composed by me and others, (as in the sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uey hereof, your Lordship may well perceiue) may not by any meanes passe, without the malignitie of some maliti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous <hi>Momus,</hi> whose malice (being as toothsome as the <hi>Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders</hi> sting) couched in the progres of a wayfayring mans passage, might make him retire though almost at his iourneyes end. Two speci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all <hi>Motiues</hi> haue imbouldened me (right Honorable) in this my proceeding. First, for that I consider, that as the body cannot bee without the shadow: so <hi>Homer</hi> (the Prince of Poets) may not be without a <hi>Zoilist:</hi> The second &amp; last is (the most forcible motiue) I know, (not onely by report, but also by experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment) your Lordship, to bee not onely <hi>Philomusus</hi> a louer of the <hi>Muses,</hi> and of learning: but <hi>Philomathes,</hi> a personage alway desirous, (though in all Arts sufficiently skilfull) to come to a more high perfection or <hi>Summum bonum.</hi> I will not trouble your Lordship with to to tedious circumstances, onely I humbly intreat your Lordship (in the name of many) to patronage this work with no lesse acceptance, then I with a willing and kinde hart dedicate it. So shall I think the <hi>initium</hi> of this worke not onely happely begun, but to bee <hi>finited</hi> with a more happie period.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Your Honours deuoted in all dutie, Thomas Morley.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div n="tenor" type="musical_part">
                  <div type="songs_of_five_parts">
                     <div type="song">
                        <pb facs="tcp:173820:35"/>
                        <head>Of 5. TENOR.</head>
                        <byline>Michaell Este.</byline>
                        <p>
                           <gap reason="music">
                              <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                           </gap> HEnce Stars, ij. to dim of light, to ij you dazel but the sight, you teach to grope by night, to ij. you dazel but the sight, you teach to grope by night, excelling you so far, Then <hi>Phebus</hi> wipt his eyes, then ij. and <hi>Zephir</hi> cleer'd the Skies, in sweet accented cries. Then sang the shepherds &amp; Nymphs of <hi>Dia╌na,</hi> Nymphs: ij. Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌ana,</hi> Long: ij. faire <hi>Ori╌ana,</hi> Long: ij. faire <hi>Ori╌ana,</hi> Long: ij. faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>This song being sent to late, and all the other printed, I plast it before the rest, rather then to leaue it out.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="1" type="song">
                        <pb facs="tcp:173820:35"/>
                        <head>Of 5. I. TENOR.</head>
                        <byline>Daniell Norcome.</byline>
                        <p>
                           <gap reason="music">
                              <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                           </gap> WIth Angels face and brightnesse, and orient hew, faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na</hi> shining, with nimble foote she tripped, {repeat} o're hills and mountaines, with nimble foote she trip╌ped, o're hills and moun╌taines, hard by <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>a╌nas,</hi> fountaines, this is that maiden <hi>Queene,</hi> {repeat} of the Fayrie land, with scepter in her hand, {repeat} the Faunes and Satires dauncing, did shew their nimble nimble lightnesse, {repeat} Faire <hi>Nais</hi> and the Nimphs did leaue their bowers, and brought their baskets full of flowers. Then sang the shepherds and Nimphs of <hi>Di╌a╌na,</hi> Long liue, long liue faire <hi>Ori╌a╌na.</hi> Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na.</hi> {repeat} {repeat}</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="2" type="song">
                        <pb facs="tcp:173820:36"/>
                        <head>Of 5. II. TENOR.</head>
                        <byline>Iohn Mundy.</byline>
                        <p>
                           <gap reason="music">
                              <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                           <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>Ightly she whipped o're the dales, she ij. making the woods proud with her presence, ij. gently she trode y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> flowres, ij. ij. &amp; they as gently kist her tender feet, the birds in their best language bad her welcome, ij. being proud that <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na</hi> heard their song: the cloue foot Satires singing, made Musick to the Faunes a dauncing, &amp; both to gether with an emphasis, sang <hi>O╌ri╌a╌nas</hi> praises, ij. ij. whilst the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyning woods with melody, with melody, did entertaine their sweet sweet harmony. ij. sweet sweet harmony. Then sang the sheperds
<pb facs="tcp:173820:36"/>
                           <gap reason="music">
                              <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                           </gap> and Nimphes of <hi>Dia╌na,</hi> the Nimphes of <hi>Dia╌na,</hi> the Nimphes, ij. of <hi>Dia╌na,</hi> ij. Long liue faire <hi>Ori╌a╌na,</hi> ij. faire <hi>O╌ria╌na,</hi> ij. faire <hi>Ori╌a╌na,</hi> ij. faire <hi>O╌ri╌ana.</hi> faire <hi>Ori╌a╌na.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="3" type="song">
                        <pb facs="tcp:173820:37"/>
                        <head>Of 5. III. TENOR.</head>
                        <byline>Ellis Gibbons.</byline>
                        <p>
                           <gap reason="music">
                              <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                           </gap> LOng liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌ana,</hi> Heark, did you euer heare so sweet a singing, They sing young Loue, The Nimphs vnto the woods, ij. Ther was a note well taken, O, good, Hark, how ioyfully, how ioyfully tis ditti'd, how ioyful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly tis ditti'd, ij. A Queene &amp; Song most excellently fitted, I neuer saw, ij. a fairer, I neuer heard a ra╌rer. Then sing ye Shepherds and Nimphes of <hi>Di╌a╌na,</hi> Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na.</hi> ij. Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na.</hi> ij. Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na.</hi> Faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="4" type="song">
                        <pb facs="tcp:173820:37"/>
                        <head>Of 5. IIII. TENOR.</head>
                        <byline>Iohn Benet.</byline>
                        <p>
                           <gap reason="music">
                              <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                           </gap> ALL cre'tures now are merry merry {repeat} {repeat} {repeat} {repeat} {repeat} {repeat} {repeat} {repeat} minded, The shepherds daughters playing, {repeat} The Nimphes are Fa la laing, {repeat} The Nimphs are Fa la la la la laing, yond bugle was wel win╌ded, At <hi>Orianaes</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sence each thing smileth, the flowres themselues discouer, {repeat} Birds ouer hir do ho╌uer, Musick the time beguileth, {repeat} See wher she comes, {repeat} with flowry garlands crowned, Queene of all queenes re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowned, renowned. Then sang the sheperds &amp; Nimphs of <hi>Diana,</hi> Nimphs of <hi>Diana,</hi> long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na,</hi> {repeat} {repeat} faire <hi>Ori╌a╌na.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="5" type="song">
                        <pb facs="tcp:173820:38"/>
                        <head>Of 5. V. TENOR.</head>
                        <byline>Iohn Hilton.</byline>
                        <p>
                           <gap reason="music">
                              <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                           </gap> FAire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na,</hi> {repeat} {repeat} Tripped a long the verdant greene, the verdant greene, {repeat} The Faunes and Satires, {repeat} running out, running out, Skipped and danced, {repeat} {repeat} round about, round a╌bout, Flora forsooke hir pain╌ted bowrs, Flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra forsooke hir bowres, And made a Coronet a Coronet of flowres. {repeat} of flowers. a Coronet of flowres. Then sang the Nimphes the Nimphes, of chast <hi>Di╌a╌na,</hi> of chast <hi>Di╌a╌na,</hi> Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na,</hi> faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na,</hi> Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na,</hi> Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="6" type="song">
                        <pb facs="tcp:173820:38"/>
                        <head>Of 5. VI. TENOR.</head>
                        <byline>George Marson.</byline>
                        <p>
                           <gap reason="music">
                              <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                           </gap> THe Nimphs and shepheards daunced, La╌uoltos in a da╌zy tapstred vally, Loue loue from their face lamps glaunced, Till wantonly they dally, Till wantonly they dally, Then in a Rose bankt ally, bright Maiestie aduanced, {repeat} {repeat} A crowne grac't Virgin whom all peo╌ple honor, all people honor, They leaue their sport amazed, Runne all, runne all to looke, run all to looke vpon hir, A moment scarce they ga╌zed, Ere beau╌ties splendor all their eies had dazed, {repeat} desire to see yet euer fixed on hir. Then sang the Shepherds &amp; Nimphs of <hi>Di╌a╌na,</hi> Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na.</hi> {repeat} liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌ana, O╌ri╌a╌na,</hi> {repeat} {repeat}</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="7" type="song">
                        <pb facs="tcp:173820:39"/>
                        <head>Of 5. VII. TENOR.</head>
                        <byline>Richard Carlton.</byline>
                        <p>
                           <gap reason="music">
                              <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                           </gap> CAlme was the aire, and cleere the skye, Faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na</hi> passing by, <hi>Ori:</hi> ij Ouer the downes to I╌da plains ij. Wher heau'n born sisters with their traines, Did all attend hir sacred beau╌ty, Striuing to excell in duty, to ex: ij. Satirs and Nimphs dauncing together, dauncing together, Shepherds triumphing, triumphing flocking thether, Seeing their sou'raigne mistris ther, their so: &amp;c. That kept their flocks &amp; them from feare, ij. With hie strayn'd voice, And harts re╌ioyce, ij. Thus sang the shepherds and the Nimphs of <hi>Di╌a╌na,</hi> Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na,</hi> Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na,</hi> faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na,</hi> ij. Long liue faire <hi>Ori╌a╌na, O╌ri╌a-</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="8" type="song">
                        <pb facs="tcp:173820:39"/>
                        <head>Of 5. VIII. TENOR.</head>
                        <byline>Iohn Holmes.</byline>
                        <p>
                           <gap reason="music">
                              <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                           </gap> THus bonny bootes the birth day cele╌brated, celebrated, Of her his Lady deerest, {repeat} Lady deerest, Faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na,</hi> which to his hart was neerest, The Nymphs &amp; shepherds feasted, With clowted creame were, {repeat} clowted creame were, &amp; to sing, were requested, {repeat} reque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sted, Lo heere the faire cre╌a╌ted (Quoth he) the worlds chiefe goddesse, Sing then, sing then, the &amp;c. for she is Bonny boots sweet Mistres. Then sang the she<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perds &amp; Nymphs of <hi>Di╌a╌na,</hi> of <hi>Di╌a╌na,</hi> Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na.</hi> faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na,</hi> {repeat} {repeat} {repeat} Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na.</hi> {repeat} {repeat}</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="9" type="song">
                        <pb facs="tcp:173820:40"/>
                        <head>Of 5. IX. TENOR.</head>
                        <byline>Richard Nicolson.</byline>
                        <p>
                           <gap reason="music">
                              <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                           </gap> SIng sheperds all, and in your roundelaies, and in: ij. and in your rounde╌laies, and: ij. your roundelaies, sing onely of faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌naes</hi> praise, faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌naes</hi> praise, sing onely: ij. of faire <hi>O╌ri╌anaes</hi> praise. The gods aboue will help to beare a part, will help to beare a part, the gods: ij. will help to beare a part, the gods aboue will help to beare a part, And men below, will trie their greatest art, and men below, below, will trie their greatest art, their greatest art, Though neither gods nor men can well ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hly, can well apply, can, ij. though neither gods nor men can well ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply, can: ij. Fit song or tune to praise her worthely, her worthely, fit
<pb facs="tcp:173820:40"/>
                           <gap reason="music">
                              <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                           </gap> song or tune, fit song or tune to praise her worthely, to praise her worthely. Then sang the shepherds, then sang the shepherds, then: ij. the shepherds, and Nimphes of <hi>Di╌a╌na,</hi> of <hi>Di╌a╌na,</hi> Long liue faire <hi>Ori╌ana,</hi> faire <hi>O╌ri╌ana,</hi> Long: ij. Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na.</hi> Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na,</hi> faire <hi>Ori╌ana,</hi> Then sang the shepherds, then sang {repeat} then sang the shepheards, then {repeat} and Nymphes of <hi>Diana,</hi> of <hi>Di╌a╌na,</hi> Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na.</hi> Long liue, ij. Long {repeat} Long {repeat} Long {repeat} faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="10" type="song">
                        <pb facs="tcp:173820:41"/>
                        <head>Of 5. X. TENOR.</head>
                        <byline>Thomas Tomkins.</byline>
                        <p>
                           <gap reason="music">
                              <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                           </gap> THE Faunes and Satirs, Satirs trip╌ping, With liuely Nymphes, with: ij. ij ij. Of fresh coole brooks, coole brooks, of: ij. of: ij. and fountaines, And those of woods and mountaines, Like Roes came nimbly skiping, came: ij. By signes, by signes their mirth vnripping, ij. ij. My faire Queene, ij. they pre╌sen╌ted, they presented, In peaces armes, with <hi>Amaltheas</hi> twentie, twentie, with: ij. Brim full of wealthie plentie, of wealthie plentie, And still to giue frequented, to giue frequented, to: ij. With bare gifts not contented, not: ij. ij. ij. cōtēted. The de╌my gods pray to the gods, the: ij.
<pb facs="tcp:173820:41"/>
                           <gap reason="music">
                              <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                           </gap> supernall, ij. the: ij. the: ij. Her life, Her wealth, Her fame, may be Eternall. ii Her life, Her wealth, Her fame, may be Eternall, Her life, Her wealth, Her fame, Her fame may be Eternall, Her life, Her wealth, Her fame, ij. may be Eternall, may: ij. ij. Eternall, may: ij. Then sang the shepherds and Nimphes of <hi>Di╌a╌na,</hi> and: ij. and: ij. Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌ana. Ori╌a╌na.</hi> Long: ij Long: ij. Long: ij. Long: ij. <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="11" type="song">
                        <pb facs="tcp:173820:42"/>
                        <head>Of 5. XI. TENOR.</head>
                        <byline>Michaell Cauendish.</byline>
                        <p>
                           <gap reason="music">
                              <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                           </gap> COme gentil swains &amp; shepherds daintie daughters, adorn'de with cour╌tesie &amp; comely duties, Come gentle: ij. adorn'd with cour╌tesie, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorn'd with courtesie &amp; comely du╌ties, Come sing &amp; ioy &amp; grace with louely laughters, Come sing: ij. The birth day of the beauties, of beauties. Then sang the shepherds &amp; Nymphs of Diana, Long liue O╌riana, Long liue faire Oriana, ij. Long liue faire Ori╌a╌na. Then sang the shepherds &amp; Nymphs of Di╌a╌na, Long liue O╌ri╌ana, Long liue faire O╌ria╌na, ij. Long liue faire O╌ri╌ana. <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na,</hi> Long &amp;c. ij. ij. ij. faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="12" type="song">
                        <pb facs="tcp:173820:42"/>
                        <head>Of 5. XII. TENOR.</head>
                        <byline>William Cobbold.</byline>
                        <p>
                           <gap reason="music">
                              <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                           </gap> WIth wrethes of rose &amp; lawrell, Withdraw your selues ye shepherds from your bowres, And straw the path with flowrs, ij. the Nimphs are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, Sweetly the birds are chirping, the swift beasts run╌ning, ij. run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, ij. ij. As all amaz'd they stand, ij. still gazing, To see such bright stars blazing, bla╌zing, Lodian brauely treading, hir daintie daughter leading, The powres deuine to hir doe vale their bonnets, to her &amp;c. Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare your selues to sound your past'rall son╌nets, ij. ij. Then sang the shepherds &amp; Nimphes of <hi>Di╌a╌na,</hi> ij. Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na,</hi> ij.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="13" type="song">
                        <pb facs="tcp:173820:43"/>
                        <head>Of 5. XIII. TENOR.</head>
                        <byline>Thomas Morley.</byline>
                        <p>
                           <gap reason="music">
                              <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                           </gap> ARise: Deuise, {repeat} deuise some honour for her sake, by mirth to banish weeping, to banish weeping, Loe where she comes, A Prince, {repeat} A Prince, a Prince of beauty rich and rare, for her de╌lighting, Pretends to goe a Maying, You stately Nymphs draw neere, draw neere, and strew your pathes with flow'rs, your: {repeat} In you her trust reposes. {repeat} Then sang the shepherds and Nimphs of <hi>Di╌a╌na,</hi> Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na,</hi> {repeat} {repeat} Long liue, Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na.</hi> Then sang the:</p>
                     </div>
                     <trailer>Heere endeth the songs of fiue parts.</trailer>
                  </div>
                  <div type="songs_of_six_parts">
                     <div n="14" type="song">
                        <pb facs="tcp:173820:43"/>
                        <head>Of 6. XIIII. TENOR.</head>
                        <byline>Iohn Farmer.</byline>
                        <p>
                           <gap reason="music">
                              <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                           </gap> FAire Nymphs, ij. I heard one telling, faire, &amp;c. <hi>Dianaes</hi> traine are hunting, in this chace, to beautifie the place, the place, The Faunes are running, The shepherds their pipes tuneing, their pipes tuneing, tuneing, The Lambs amazed leaue of their grasing, And blind their eies, ij. with ga╌sing, whilst the earths God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>desse doth draw neere, doth draw neere your places, Attended by the Muses, ij. &amp; y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Graces, y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Graces. Then sang the shepherds and Nimphs, the shepherds and Nymphs: Then sang the shepherds, ij. ij. and Nymphs of <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>a╌na,</hi> Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na,</hi> ij. faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na.</hi> Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="15" type="song">
                        <pb facs="tcp:173820:44"/>
                        <head>Of 6. XV. TENOR.</head>
                        <byline>Iohn Wilbye.</byline>
                        <p>
                           <gap reason="music">
                              <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                           </gap> THe Lady <hi>Ori╌ana,</hi> ij. Was dight all in the treasures, all in the treasures of <hi>Guiana,</hi> Was, ij. And on her Grace a thousand Graces tended, a thousand, thousand Graces ten╌ded, And thus sang they, faire Queene of peace &amp; plenty, The fairest queene, the: ij. of twentie, Then with an Oliue wreath for peace renowned, Her Virgins head they crowned; Which ceremony ended, ij. Which ceremony en╌ded, Vnto her grace the thousād Graces bended. Then sang the shepherds &amp; Nimphs of <hi>Di╌ana,</hi> Long liue faire <hi>Ori╌a╌na,</hi> faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na.</hi> Long: ij. faire <hi>O╌ri╌ana.</hi> Long liue faire <hi>O╌ria╌na.</hi> ij. faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na.</hi> Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na,</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="16" type="song">
                        <pb facs="tcp:173820:44"/>
                        <head>Of 6. XVI. TENOR.</head>
                        <byline>Thomas Hunt.</byline>
                        <p>
                           <gap reason="music">
                              <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                           </gap> HArk! hark! hark, ij. did yee euer heare so sweet a singing? ij. did yee euer heare so sweet a singing? They sing young loue to waken, The Nymphs vnto the woods, ij. their Queene are bringing, ij. There was a note well taken, ij. hark hark: O most de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinely ditti'd, ij. O &amp;c. A Queene and song most excellently fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, ij. most ex╌cellent, most excellently fitted, I neuer saw a fairer, ij. a fairer, I neuer heard a rarer, ij. a rarer. Then sang the Nymphs &amp; shepherds of <hi>Di╌a╌na,</hi> Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌ana,</hi> Long &amp;c. Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na,</hi> Long &amp;c. faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="17" type="song">
                        <pb facs="tcp:173820:45"/>
                        <head>Of 6. XVII. TENOR.</head>
                        <byline>Thomas Weelkes.</byline>
                        <p>
                           <gap reason="music">
                              <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                           <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S <hi>Vesta</hi> was from <hi>Latmos</hi> hill descen╌ding, from <hi>Latmos</hi> hill descen╌ding, descending, She spied a maiden Queene the same ascending, the same ascen╌ding, the same ascending, the same as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cending, Attended on by all the shepherds swain, ij. To whom <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anaes</hi> dar╌lings, Came running downe amaine, a╌maine, ij. ij. Came running downe amaine, ij. First two by two, then three by three together, Leauing their God╌desse ha╌sted thether, And mingling with the shepherds of her traine, of her train, With mirthfull tunes, her presence entertaine. Then sang the shepherds and Nymphs of <hi>Di╌a╌na,</hi> Nymphs
<pb facs="tcp:173820:45"/>
                           <gap reason="music">
                              <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                           </gap> of <hi>Diana,</hi> Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na.</hi> ij. ij. faire <hi>O╌ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>a╌na,</hi> Long liue faire <hi>Ori╌ana,</hi> liue long, Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na,</hi> faire <hi>Ori╌a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na,</hi> ij. ij. Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na,</hi> ij. faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="18" type="song">
                        <pb facs="tcp:173820:46"/>
                        <head>Of 6. XVIII. TENOR.</head>
                        <byline>Iohn Milton.</byline>
                        <p>
                           <gap reason="music">
                              <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                           </gap> FAire <hi>Ori╌an</hi> in the morne, in the morne, before the day was borne, with veluet steps on ground, which made nor print nor sound, which: ij. nor sound, Would see her Nymphs a bed, what liues those Ladies led, what: ij. what: ij. those: ij. what: ij. The Roses blushing sayd, O stay, O stay thou shepherds mayd, O stay: ij. And on a sodaine all, they rose and heard her call. they: ij they: ij Then sang those shepherds and Nymphs of <hi>Diana,</hi> and Nymphs: ij Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na,</hi> Long: ij. Long: ij. Long: ij.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="19" type="song">
                        <pb facs="tcp:173820:46"/>
                        <head>Of 6. XIX. TENOR.</head>
                        <byline>Ellis Gibbons.</byline>
                        <p>
                           <gap reason="music">
                              <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                           </gap> ROund about her Charret with all admiring strains, The <hi>Hya╌des</hi> and <hi>Drya╌des</hi> ij. Lo how the gods in reuells, do ac╌cord, in reuells do accord, Whilst doth each goddesse melodies af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford, ij. whilst doth each Goddesse melo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies afford, Now <hi>Baccus</hi> is consorting, <hi>Sil╌ua╌nus</hi> fals to sporting, <hi>Amphi╌ons</hi> harp's reporting. Long liue faire <hi>Ori╌a╌na.</hi> ij. Long liue faire <hi>Ori╌a╌na.</hi> Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na.</hi> ij. ij. ij. Long liue faire <hi>Oria╌na.</hi> Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na. O╌ri╌a╌na.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="20" type="song">
                        <pb facs="tcp:173820:47"/>
                        <head>Of 6. XX. TENOR.</head>
                        <byline>George Kyrbie.</byline>
                        <p>
                           <gap reason="music">
                              <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                           </gap> WIth An: Faire <hi>Ori╌ana,</hi> ij. faire <hi>Ori╌ana</hi> shining, with nimble foot she tripped, o're hils &amp; mountaines, o're: ij. At last in dale she rested, hard by <hi>Dianaes</hi> fountaines, <hi>Dia:</hi> ij. With septer in her hand, ij. The Faunes and Satirs dauncing, ij. did shew their nimble lightnes, Faire <hi>Nais</hi> &amp; the Nimphs did leaue their bowers. Then sang the shepherds &amp; Nimphs of <hi>Dia╌na,</hi> Nymphs of <hi>Diana,</hi> Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌ana.</hi> ij. faire <hi>O╌ri╌ana,</hi> Long liue faire <hi>Ori╌a╌na,</hi> ij. faire <hi>Oriana,</hi> Lōg liue faire <hi>Ori╌ana,</hi> faire <hi>Oriana.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="21" type="song">
                        <pb facs="tcp:173820:47"/>
                        <head>Of 6. XXI. TENOR.</head>
                        <byline>Robert Iones.</byline>
                        <p>
                           <gap reason="music">
                              <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                           </gap> FAire <hi>Oria╌na:</hi> Lay softly down a sleeping, Lay: ij. Lay ij. But hearing y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> the world was grown vnholly, But ij. to weeping, to ij. So wakt, so wakt, she sight, ij. ij. ij. &amp; with crost armes, sate drincking teares for others harms, sate ij. and shepherds of <hi>Diana,</hi> and ij. Long liue faire <hi>Oria╌na,</hi> Long ij. Long: ij. Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌ana.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="22" type="song">
                        <pb facs="tcp:173820:48"/>
                        <head>Of 6. XXII. TENOR.</head>
                        <byline>Iohn Lisley.</byline>
                        <p>
                           <gap reason="music">
                              <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                           </gap> FAire <hi>Citharea</hi> presents her Doues, <hi>Minerua</hi> singeth, <hi>Ioue</hi> giues a crown, a garland <hi>Iuno</hi> bringeth, a garland <hi>Iuno</hi> bringeth, <hi>Fame</hi> sūmōs each ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesti╌all power, celestiall power, To bring their gifts to <hi>Orians</hi> bower, to <hi>O╌ri╌a╌naes</hi> bower. Then sang the shepherds &amp; Nymphs of <hi>Dia╌na,</hi> Long liue saire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na,</hi> Long ij. faire <hi>Ori╌a╌na,</hi> Then sang the shepherds and Nymphs of <hi>Dia╌na,</hi> Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na,</hi> Long: ij. faire <hi>Ori╌a╌na.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="23" type="song">
                        <pb facs="tcp:173820:48"/>
                        <head>Of 6. XXIII. <hi>TENOR.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <byline>Thomas Morley.</byline>
                        <p>
                           <gap reason="music">
                              <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                           </gap> HArd by a Cristall: The birds they finely chirped, ij. the ij. The windes were stilled, ij. Sweetly with these accenting, ij. ij. The aire was filled, Which heauen for her reserueth, ij. ij. Leaue shepherds your lambs keeping, Vpon the barren mountaine, ij. the &amp;c. And Nymphs attend on hir &amp; leaue your bowers. Then sang the shepherds &amp; Nymphs, ij. and Nymphs of <hi>Di╌a╌na.</hi> Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na</hi> ij. ij. Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na.</hi> ij. faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na.</hi> Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na,</hi> faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="24" type="song">
                        <pb facs="tcp:173820:49"/>
                        <head>Of 6 XXIIII. TENOR.</head>
                        <byline>Edward Iohnson.</byline>
                        <p>
                           <gap reason="music">
                              <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                           </gap> COme blessed Bird, Come blessed Bird and with thy sugred rellish, Help our declining quire now to embellish, For Bonny bootes, for Bonny bootes that so a loft would fetch it, that &amp;c. Oh he is dead, he is dead, and none of vs can reach it, and I, <hi>Elpin,</hi> and I and <hi>Dorus,</hi> for fault of better will serue in the <hi>Corus,</hi> Begin and we will follow thee in order. Then sang the Woodborne minstrell of <hi>Di╌a╌na,</hi> Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na.</hi> ij. Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na.</hi> ij. Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:173820:49"/>
                  <p>QVINTVS.</p>
                  <p>MADRIGALES The Triumphes of Oriana, to 5. and 6. voices: com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posed by diuers seuerall <hi>aucthors.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Newly published by Thomas Morley Batcheler of Musick, and one of the gentlemen of her</hi> Maiesties honorable Chappell.</p>
                  <p>1601.</p>
                  <p>IN LONDON PRINTED BY THOMAS ESTE, the assigne of Thomas Morley.</p>
                  <p>¶ Cum priuilegio Regiae Maiestatis.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="table_of_contents">
                  <pb facs="tcp:173820:50"/>
                  <head>¶ The Table of all the Madrigales contained in these bookes, vvith the names of their seuerall authors.</head>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Songs of 5. parts.</head>
                     <list>
                        <item>Hence Stars you dazell but the sight. <hi>Michaell Este.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>VVIth Angells face and brightnesse. I <hi>Daniell Norcome.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Lightly she whipped o're y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> dales. II <hi>Iohn Mundy Batcheler of Musick</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Long liue faire <hi>Oriana.</hi> III <hi>Ellis Gibbons.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>All creatures now are merry. IIII <hi>Iohn Benet.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Faire <hi>Oriana</hi> beauties Queene. V <hi>Iohn Hilton. Batcheler of Musick</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>The Nymphs and shepherds danced. VI <hi>George Marson. Batch. of Musick</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Calme was the Aire. VII <hi>Richard Carlton. Batch. of Musick</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Thus bonny bootes the birth day. VIII <hi>Iohn Holmes.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Sing shepherds all. IX <hi>Richard Nicolson.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>The Faunes and Satirs tripping. X <hi>Thomas Tomkins.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Come gentle swaines. XI <hi>Michaell Cauendish.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Withdraw your selues yee shepherds. XII <hi>William Cobbold.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Arise awake you silly shepherds sleping. XIII <hi>Thomas Morley Batch. of Musick</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Song of 6. parts.</head>
                     <list>
                        <item>Faire Nymphes I heard one telling. XIIII <hi>Iohn Farmer.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>The lady <hi>Oriana.</hi> XV <hi>Iohn Wilby.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Hark! hark, did you euer heare &amp;c. XVI <hi>Thomas Hunt. Batch. of Musick</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>As <hi>Ʋesta</hi> was from <hi>Latmos</hi> hill &amp;c. XVII <hi>Thomas Weelks.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Faire <hi>Orian</hi> in the morne. XVIII <hi>Iohn Milton.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Round about her Charret &amp;c. XIX <hi>Ellis Gibbons.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>With Angells face and brightnesse. XX <hi>George Kirbye.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Faire <hi>Oriana</hi> seeming to wink at folly. XXI <hi>Robert Iones.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Faire <hi>Citharea</hi> presents her Doues &amp;c. XXII <hi>Iohn Lisley.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Hard by a Christall fountaine. XXIII <hi>Thomas Morley. Batch. of Musick</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Come blessed Byrd &amp;c. XXIIII <hi>Edward Iohnson. Batch of Musick</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
               <div type="dedication">
                  <pb facs="tcp:173820:50"/>
                  <head>TO THE RIGHT HO<seg rend="sup">norable</seg>. THE LORD Charles Howard <hi>Earle of Notingham, Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron</hi> of <hi>Effingham,</hi> Knight of the Noble order of the <hi>Garter,</hi> Lord high <hi>Admirall</hi> of <hi>England, Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and <hi>Wales, &amp;c.</hi> And one of her Majesties most honorable Priuie Counsell.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>RIGHT HO<seg rend="sup">norable</seg>.</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Haue aduentured to dedicate these few discordant tunes to be censured by the ingenious disposition of your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ships Honorable rare perfection, perswading my selfe, that these labours, composed by me and others, (as in the sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uey hereof, your Lordship may well perceiue) may not by any meanes passe, without the malignitie of some maliti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous <hi>Momus,</hi> whose malice (being as toothsome as the <hi>Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders</hi> sting) couched in the progres of a wayfayring mans passage, might make him retire though almost at his iourneyes end. Two speci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all <hi>Motiues</hi> haue imbouldened me (right Honorable) in this my proceeding. First, for that I consider, that as the body cannot bee without the shadow: so <hi>Homer</hi> (the Prince of Poets) may not be without a <hi>Zoilist:</hi> The second &amp; last is (the most forcible motiue) I know, (not onely by report, but also by experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment) your Lordship, to bee not onely <hi>Philomusus</hi> a louer of the <hi>Muses,</hi> and of learning: but <hi>Philomathes,</hi> a personage alway desirous, (though in all Arts sufficiently skilfull) to come to a more high perfection or <hi>Summum bonum.</hi> I will not trouble your Lordship with to to tedious circumstances, onely I humbly intreat your Lordship (in the name of many) to patronage this work with no lesse acceptance, then I with a willing and kinde hart dedicate it. So shall I think the <hi>initium</hi> of this worke not onely happely begun, but to bee <hi>finited</hi> with a more happie period.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Your Honours deuoted in all dutie, Thomas Morley.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div n="quintus" type="musical_part">
                  <div type="songs_of_five_parts">
                     <div type="song">
                        <pb facs="tcp:173820:51"/>
                        <head>Of 5. QVINTVS.</head>
                        <byline>Michaell Este.</byline>
                        <p>
                           <gap reason="music">
                              <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                           </gap> HEnce Stars, you dazel but the fight, you teach to grope by night, you dazel but the sight, you teach to grope by night, you: ij. to grope by night, See heere the shepherds star, then <hi>Phebus</hi> wipt his eyes, then <hi>Phaebus</hi> wipt his eies, &amp; <hi>Zephirus</hi> cleer'd the Skies, in sweet accented cries. Then sang the shepherds &amp; Nymphs of <hi>Dia╌na.</hi> Nymphs: ij. Long liue faire <hi>Ori╌ana,</hi> Long: ij. Long: ij. Long: ij. Long: ij. Long: ij. faire <hi>Ori╌a╌na.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>This song being sent to late, and all the other printed, I plast it before the rest, rather then to leaue it out,</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="1" type="song">
                        <pb facs="tcp:173820:51"/>
                        <head>Of 5. I. QVINTVS.</head>
                        <byline>Daniell Norcome.</byline>
                        <p>
                           <gap reason="music">
                              <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                           </gap> WIth Angels face &amp; bright╌nes, &amp; brightnes, with: ij. &amp; orient hew, faire <hi>Ori╌a╌na</hi> shining, with nimble foote she tripped, o're hills &amp; moun╌taines, o're: ij. o're: ij. at last in dale she rested: this is y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> maiden <hi>Queene,</hi> of the Fayrie land, with scepter in her hand, ij. {repeat} the Faunes and Satires dauncing, did shew their nimble nimble lightnes, {repeat} Faire <hi>Nais</hi> &amp; y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Nimphs did leaue their bowers, did leaue their bowers, &amp; brought their baskets full of hearbs &amp; flowers. Thē sang the shepherds &amp; Nimphs of <hi>Di╌a╌na,</hi> Then: ij. Long liue, ij. ij. long: ij. ij. ij. faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="2" type="song">
                        <pb facs="tcp:173820:52"/>
                        <head>Of 5. II. QVINTVS.</head>
                        <byline>Iohn Mundy.</byline>
                        <p>
                           <gap reason="music">
                              <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                           <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>Ightly she whipped o're the dales, ij. ore the dales, making the woods proud with her presence, ij. with her pre╌sence, gently she trode y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> flowres, the flowres, &amp; they as gently kist her tender feet, the birds in their best language bad her welcome, ij. being proud that <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na</hi> heard their song: the cloue foot Satires singing, made Musick to the Faunes a dauncing, and both to gether with an emphasis, sang <hi>O╌ri╌a╌nas</hi> prai╌ses, ij. ij. whilst the aioyning woods with me╌lo╌dy, with melody, did entertain their sweet harmony, their sweet harmony. Then
<pb facs="tcp:173820:52"/>
                           <gap reason="music">
                              <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                           </gap> sang the sheperds and Nimphes of <hi>Diana,</hi> the Nimphes of <hi>Diana,</hi> the ij. ij. Long liue faire <hi>Ori╌a╌na,</hi> ij. <hi>Ori╌a╌na,</hi> ij. ij. ij. faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na,</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="3" type="song">
                        <pb facs="tcp:173820:53"/>
                        <head>Of 5. III. QVINTVS.</head>
                        <byline>Ellis Gibbons.</byline>
                        <p>
                           <gap reason="music">
                              <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                           </gap> LOng liue faire <hi>O╌ria╌na,</hi> Heark, did you e╌uer heare so sweet a sing╌ing, They sing young Loue to wake, The Nimphs vn╌to the woods, ij. ij. the woods, their Queene are bringing, Ther was a note well taken, O, good, Hark, how ioyful╌ly, how ioyfully tis ditti'd, ij. how ioyfully tis ditti'd, tis ditti'd, A Queene &amp; Song most excel╌lently fit╌ted, I ne╌uer heard a rarer, I neuer heard, I neuer saw a fai╌rer. Then sing ye Shepherds and Nimphes of <hi>Di╌a╌na,</hi> Nimphs &amp;c. Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na,</hi> ij. Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na,</hi> ij. ij. faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="4" type="song">
                        <pb facs="tcp:173820:53"/>
                        <head>Of 5. IIII. QVINTVS.</head>
                        <byline>Iohn Benet.</byline>
                        <p>
                           <gap reason="music">
                              <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                           </gap> ALL cre'tures now are merry merry {repeat} {repeat} {repeat} {repeat} {repeat} {repeat} {repeat} minded, are {repeat} {repeat} {repeat} {repeat} {repeat} minded, The shepherds daughters playing, {repeat} The Nimphes are Fa la laing, {repeat} {repeat} Yond bugle was wel win╌ded, At <hi>Orianaes</hi> pre╌sence each thing smi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth, the flowres themselues discouer, {repeat} Birds ouer hir do ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, Musicke the time beguileth, See wher she comes, {repeat} with flowry garlands crowned, Queene of all queenes renowned. {repeat} Then sang the shepherds &amp; Nimphs of <hi>Di╌ana,</hi> Nimphes of <hi>Diana,</hi> long liue faire <hi>O╌ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>a╌na,</hi> Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na, O╌ri╌a╌na,</hi> Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na,</hi> faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="5" type="song">
                        <pb facs="tcp:173820:54"/>
                        <head>Of 5. V. QVINTVS.</head>
                        <byline>Iohn Hilton.</byline>
                        <p>
                           <gap reason="music">
                              <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                           </gap> FAire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na</hi> beauties Queene, faire <hi>Ori╌a╌na,</hi> {repeat} beauties Queene, Tripped a long the verdant greene, the verdant greene, along &amp;c. The Faunes and Satires, {repeat} running out, {repeat} Skipped and dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, {repeat} round a╌bout, {repeat} {repeat} Flora forsooke hir painted bowrs, forsooke hir pain╌ted bowres, hir pain╌ted bowres, And made a Coronet of flowres. of flowers, and &amp;c. Then sang the Nimphs of chast <hi>Di╌a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na,</hi> Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na,</hi> Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na,</hi> faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na,</hi> Long, Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na,</hi> faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="6" type="song">
                        <pb facs="tcp:173820:54"/>
                        <head>Of 5. VI. QVINTVS.</head>
                        <byline>George Marson.</byline>
                        <p>
                           <gap reason="music">
                              <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                           </gap> THe Nimphs and shepheards daunced, La╌uoltos in a da╌zy tapstred vally, Loue loue loue from their face lamps glaunced, Till wantonly they dally, {repeat} Then in a Rose, a Rose bankt ally, Bright Maiestie, bright Maiestie aduanced, {repeat} A crowne grac't Virgin whom all people honor, all people honor, They leaue their sport amazed, Runne all to looke vpon hir, {repeat} A moment scarce they ga╌zed, Ere beau╌ties splendor all their eies had dazed, desire to see yet euer fixed on hir. Then sang the Shepherds &amp; Nimphs of <hi>Di╌ana,</hi> Long liue faire <hi>Oria╌na.</hi> {repeat} faire <hi>Oria╌na,</hi> liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na. O╌ri╌a╌na, O╌ri╌a╌na.</hi> liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na.</hi> {repeat}</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="7" type="song">
                        <pb facs="tcp:173820:55"/>
                        <head>Of 5. VII. QVINTVS.</head>
                        <byline>Richard Carlton.</byline>
                        <p>
                           <gap reason="music">
                              <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                           </gap> CAlme was the aire, ij. and cleere the skye, Faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na</hi> pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing by, <hi>Ori:</hi> ij. Ouer the downes to I╌da plains ij. Wher heau'n born sisters with their traines, Did all attend hir sacred beauty, Striuing to excell in duty, to ex: ij. Satirs and Nimphs daun╌cing together, daun: ij together, Shepherds triumphing, ij. flocking thether, Seeing their sou'raigne mistris ther, their so: &amp;c. That kept their flocks &amp; them from feare, &amp; ij. That kept: ij. With hie strayn'd voice, And harts re╌ioyce, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce. Thus sang the sheperds and Nimphs of <hi>Dia na,</hi> long liue faire <hi>O╌ria╌na,</hi> ij. ij. Long liue faire <hi>Ori╌a╌na</hi> ij.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="8" type="song">
                        <pb facs="tcp:173820:55"/>
                        <head>Of 5. VIII. QVINTVS.</head>
                        <byline>Iohn Holmes.</byline>
                        <p>
                           <gap reason="music">
                              <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                           </gap> THus bonny bootes the birth day cele╌brated, the &amp;c. cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bra╌ted, Of her his Lady dee╌rest, {repeat} his Lady dee╌rest, Faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na,</hi> which to his hart was neerest, The Nymphs &amp; shepherds feasted, With clowted creame were, {repeat} and to sing re╌quested, {repeat} Loe heere the faire created (Quoth he) the worlds chiefe goddesse, Sing then, the &amp;c. for she is Bonny-bootes sweet Mistres. Then sang the shepherds &amp; Nymphs of <hi>Di╌a╌na,</hi> of <hi>Di╌a╌na,</hi> Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na.</hi> faire <hi>O╌ri╌a na,</hi> {repeat} {repeat} {repeat} Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na.</hi> {repeat} Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="9" type="song">
                        <pb facs="tcp:173820:56"/>
                        <head>Of 5. IX. QVINTVS.</head>
                        <byline>Richard Nicolson.</byline>
                        <p>
                           <gap reason="music">
                              <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                           </gap> SIng shepherds all, and in your rounde╌laies, your roundelaies, and in: ij. and in your roundelaies, your roundelaies, Sing onely of faire <hi>O╌ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>a╌naes</hi> praise, sing onely: ij. of faire <hi>Ori╌a╌naes</hi> praise, The gods aboue will help to beare a part, the gods: ij. the gods a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue will help to beare a part, And men below, will trie their greatest art, And ij. wil: ij. Though neither gods nor men can well apply, Though neither gods nor men can well apply, Fit song or tune to praise her worthely, fit song: ij. to praise her worthely. Then sang the shepherds, then sang the shepherds, then: ij. and Nimphes
<pb facs="tcp:173820:56"/>
                           <gap reason="music">
                              <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                           </gap> of <hi>Di╌a╌na,</hi> of <hi>Dia╌na,</hi> Long liue faire <hi>Ori╌ana,</hi> Long: ij. Long: ij. Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌ana,</hi> Long: ij. faire <hi>O╌ria╌na,</hi> Then sang the shepherds, then sang the shepheards, then ij. then sang the shepherds, and Nymphes of <hi>Diana,</hi> Long liue faire <hi>O╌riana.</hi> Long: ij. Long liue faire <hi>Ori╌ana,</hi> Long: ij. Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌ana.</hi> Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="10" type="song">
                        <pb facs="tcp:173820:57"/>
                        <head>Of 5. X. QVINTVS.</head>
                        <byline>Thomas Tomkins.</byline>
                        <p>
                           <gap reason="music">
                              <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                           </gap> THE Faunes &amp; Satirs, Satirs trip╌ping, With liuely Nymphs, with ij. ij. Of fresh coole brooks, ij. ij. ij. and fountaines, And those of woods and mountaines, Like Roes came nimbly skiping, came: ij. By signes their mirth vnripping, vn: ij. their: ij. ij. vnripping, My faire Queene, ij. they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sented, With <hi>Amaltheas</hi> twenty, ij. Brim full of welthie plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, And still to giue frequented, And: ij. frequented, With bare gifts not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented, contented, not contented, ij. ij. The de╌my gods pray to the gods supernall, the: ij. the: ij Her life, Her wealth, Her
<pb facs="tcp:173820:57"/>
                           <gap reason="music">
                              <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                           </gap> fame, may be Eternall. Eternall, Her: ij. may: ij. Her life, ij. may be Eternall, ij. Eternall, Then sang the shepherds and Nimphs of <hi>Di╌a╌na,</hi> and: ij. ij. Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌ana.</hi> ij. ij. <hi>Ori╌a╌na</hi> Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na, O╌ri╌a╌na.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="11" type="song">
                        <pb facs="tcp:173820:58"/>
                        <head>Of 5. XI. QVINTVS.</head>
                        <byline>Michaell Cauendish.</byline>
                        <p>
                           <gap reason="music">
                              <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                           </gap> COme gentle swaines and shepherds dainty daughters, Adornd with courtesie and comely duties, {repeat} adornd with courtesie, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dornd with courtesie and comely du╌ties, Come sing and ioy and grace with louely laughters, The birth day of the beauties, of beauties. Then sang the Shepherds and Nymphs of <hi>Di╌a╌na,</hi> Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na,</hi> {repeat} {repeat} faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na.</hi> Then sang the shepherds and Nymphs of <hi>Di╌a╌na,</hi> Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na.</hi> {repeat} Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na,</hi> faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="12" type="song">
                        <pb facs="tcp:173820:58"/>
                        <head>Of 5. XII. QVINTVS.</head>
                        <byline>William Cobbold.</byline>
                        <p>
                           <gap reason="music">
                              <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                           </gap> WIth wreathes of Rose &amp; lawrell, withdraw your selues ye shepherds from your bowres, and strew the path with flowres, The Nimphs are comming, Sweetly the birds are chirping, The swift beasts run╌ning, The ij. As all amazde they stand, ij. still gazing, To see such bright stars blazing, lo Dian brauely tread╌ing, her daintie daughter leading, The powres deuine to her, ij. doe vale their bonnets, Prepare your selues to sound your pasterall sonnets, ij. your pasterall sonnets, Then sang the shepherds &amp; Nymphs of Di╌a╌na, ij. Long liue faire Ori╌a╌na, ij. O╌ri╌ana, Long liue faire O╌ri╌a╌na. ij. faire O╌ri╌a╌na. ij. faire O╌ri╌a╌na.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="13" type="song">
                        <pb facs="tcp:173820:59"/>
                        <head>Of 5. XIII. QVINTVS.</head>
                        <byline>Thomas Morley.</byline>
                        <p>
                           <gap reason="music">
                              <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                           </gap> ARise, awake, awake, awake you silly shepherds sleeping, de╌uise some honour for her sake, by mirth to banish weeping, {repeat} Loe wher, Loe where she comes, Loe wher she comes in gaudie greene araying, Loe wher, loe wher she comes, she comes in gaudie greene araying, A Prince of beauty rich and rare, for her de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighting, Pretends to goe a Maying, You stately Nymphs draw neere, draw neere, and strew your pathes with flow╌ers, In you her trust repo╌ses, reposes. Then sang the shepherds and Nimphs of <hi>Di╌a╌na,</hi> Long liue, Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na,</hi> {repeat} Long liue, {repeat} Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na.</hi> {repeat} Then sang:</p>
                     </div>
                     <trailer>Heere endeth the songs of fiue parts.</trailer>
                  </div>
                  <div type="songs_of_six_parts">
                     <div n="14" type="song">
                        <pb facs="tcp:173820:59"/>
                        <head>Of 6. XIIII. QVINTVS.</head>
                        <byline>Iohn Farmer.</byline>
                        <p>
                           <gap reason="music">
                              <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                           </gap> FAire Nymphs, ij. I heard one telling, faire, &amp;c. <hi>Dianaes</hi> traine are hunting, in this chace, To beautifie the place, the place, The Faunes are running, The shepherds their pipes tuneing, ij. To shew their cunning, ij. The Lambs amazed leaue of their grasing, And blind their eies with gasing, Whilst the earths Goddesse doth draw neere your places, places, Attended by the Muse, ij. ij. Attended by the Muses and the Graces, Then sang the shepherds and Nimphs, the shepherds and Nymphs: Then sang the shep╌herds then &amp;c. and Nymphs of <hi>Di╌a╌na,</hi> Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na, O╌ri╌a╌na.</hi> Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na,</hi> Long &amp;c. ij.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="15" type="song">
                        <pb facs="tcp:173820:60"/>
                        <head>Of 6. XV. QVINTVS.</head>
                        <byline>Iohn Wilbye.</byline>
                        <p>
                           <gap reason="music">
                              <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                           </gap> THe Lady <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na,</hi> ij. Was dight all in the treasures of <hi>Gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>a╌na,</hi> all in the treasures, all: ij. And on her Grace a thousand Graces ten╌ded, a thousand Graces, Graces tended, &amp; thus sang they, faire Queene of peace &amp; plenty, The fairest queene of twentie, Then with an Oliue wreath for peace renowned, Her Virgins head they crowned; Which ceremony ended, ij. ij. Which ceremony ended, ij. Vnto her grace the thousand Graces bended. Then sang y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> shepherds, the shepherds &amp; Nimphs of <hi>Di╌ana,</hi> Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na,</hi> ij. faire <hi>O╌ria╌na,</hi> Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na.</hi> ij. faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na.</hi> ij.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="16" type="song">
                        <pb facs="tcp:173820:60"/>
                        <head>Of 6. XVI. QVINTVS.</head>
                        <byline>Thomas Hunt.</byline>
                        <p>
                           <gap reason="music">
                              <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                           </gap> HArk! ij. hark! hark! did yee euer heare, did yee euer heare so sweet so sweet a singing ij. did yee euer heare so sweet a singing? They sing young loue to wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, to waken, The Nymphs vnto the woods, ij. their Queene are bringing, There was a note well taken, well taken, ij. there &amp;c. well ta╌ken, Hark! hark! O good! O most de╌uinely ditti'd, ij. A Queene and song most excellent, most &amp;c. most ex╌cellently fitted, ij. most excellent╌ly fitted, I neuer saw a fayrer, ij. I neuer heard, I neuer heard a rarer, a rarer, I neuer heard, ij. Then sung the Nymphs &amp; shepherds of Di╌a╌na. Long liue faire O╌ri╌ana, ij. Long liue faire O╌ri╌ana, ij. faire O╌ria╌na.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="17" type="song">
                        <pb facs="tcp:173820:61"/>
                        <head>Of 6. XVII. QVINTVS.</head>
                        <byline>Thomas Weelkes.</byline>
                        <p>
                           <gap reason="music">
                              <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                           <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S <hi>Vesta</hi> Attended on by all the shepherds swain, ij. To whom <hi>Di╌anaes</hi> darlings Came running downe amaine, ij. ij. amaine, ij. amaine, Came downe amaine, Then three by three to gether Leauing their God╌desse hasted thether, And mingling with the shepheards of her traine, with the shepherds of her traine, With mirthfull tunes, ij. her presence entertaine, enter╌taine, her ij. Then sang the shepherds and Nymphs of <hi>Di╌a╌na,</hi> Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na,</hi> ij. ij. faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na,</hi> Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na,</hi> ij.
<pb facs="tcp:173820:61"/>
                           <gap reason="music">
                              <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                           </gap> faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na,</hi> Long &amp;c. ij. Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na,</hi> ij. ij. Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="18" type="song">
                        <pb facs="tcp:173820:62"/>
                        <head>Of 6. XVIII. QVINTVS.</head>
                        <byline>Iohn Milton.</byline>
                        <p>
                           <gap reason="music">
                              <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                           </gap> FAire <hi>Ori╌an</hi> in the morne, before the day was borne, in: ij. before: ij. With veluet steps on ground, which made nor print nor sound, Would see her Nymphs a bed, what liues those Ladies led, what: ij. what: ij. those: ij. those: ij. those: ij. The Roses blushing sayd, O stay thou shepherds mayd, O stay: ij. And on a sodain all, they rose and heard her call. Then sang those shepherds and Nymphs of <hi>Diana,</hi> then ij. of <hi>Di╌a╌na, Di╌a╌na, Di╌a╌na,</hi> Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na,</hi> Long: ij. Long: ij. Long: ij</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="19" type="song">
                        <pb facs="tcp:173820:62"/>
                        <head>Of 6. XIX. QVINTVS.</head>
                        <byline>Ellis Gibbons.</byline>
                        <p>
                           <gap reason="music">
                              <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                           </gap> ROund about her Charret with all admiring strains, ij. The <hi>Hya╌des</hi> and <hi>Drya╌des</hi> giue sweetest entertaynes, giue sweetest entertaines, Lo how the gods in reuells, in reuels do ac╌cord, Whilst doth each goddesse melodies afford, melodies afford, Whilst: ij. Now <hi>Baccus</hi> is consorting, <hi>Siluanus</hi> fals to sporting, <hi>Amphions</hi> harp's repor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting. To the shepherds pipes sing the Nymphs of <hi>Diana,</hi> Long liue faire <hi>Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>a╌na.</hi> ij. Long liue faire <hi>Ori╌ana.</hi> ij. Long liue faire <hi>Ori╌a╌na.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="20" type="song">
                        <pb facs="tcp:173820:63"/>
                        <head>Of 6. XX. QIVNTVS.</head>
                        <byline>George Kyrbie.</byline>
                        <p>
                           <gap reason="music">
                              <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                           </gap> WIth Angels face &amp; brightnesse, &amp; o╌rient hew, faire <hi>Oriana,</hi> ij. faire <hi>Oriana</hi> shining, With nimble foot she tripped, o're hils &amp; mountaines, o're: ij. At last in dale she rested, hard by <hi>Dianaes</hi> fountaines, ij. This is that Mayden Queene of the Fayrie land, With septer in her hand, ij. The Faunes and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirs dauncing, did shew their nimble lightnes, Faire <hi>Nais</hi> and the Nymphes did leaue their bowers, and brought their baskets full of hearbes and flowers. Then sang the shepherds &amp; Nymphs of <hi>Diana,</hi> ij. Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌ana,</hi> faire <hi>Ori╌ana,</hi> ij faire ij, Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌ana,</hi> faire <hi>Ori╌a╌na,</hi> ij. Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="21" type="song">
                        <pb facs="tcp:173820:63"/>
                        <head>Of 6. XXI. QVINTVS.</head>
                        <byline>Robert Iones.</byline>
                        <p>
                           <gap reason="music">
                              <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                           </gap> FAire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na</hi> ij. seeming to winck at folly, to: ij. faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na,</hi> ij. Lay softly down to sleeping, to sleeping, lay: ij. lay: ij. lay: ij. But hearing y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> the world was grown vnholly, but: ij. her rest was turnd to weeping, to ij. to: ij. So wakt, shee sight, ij. ij. and with crost armes, crost armes, and: ij. sate drincking teares for o╌thers harms, sate: ij. Then sang the Nymphs &amp; shepherds of <hi>Diana,</hi> &amp; ij. Long liue faire <hi>O╌ria╌na,</hi> faire <hi>Oriana,</hi> Long: ij. Long: ij. faire <hi>Oria╌na.</hi> Long: ij.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="22" type="song">
                        <pb facs="tcp:173820:64"/>
                        <head>Of 6. XXII. <hi>QVINTVS.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <byline>Iohn Lisley.</byline>
                        <p>
                           <gap reason="music">
                              <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                           </gap> FAire <hi>Citharea</hi> presents her Doues, ij. <hi>Minerua</hi> sing╌eth, <hi>Ioue</hi> giues a crowne, a garland <hi>Iuno</hi> bringeth, a gar: ij <hi>Fame</hi> sūmōs each celestiall power, <hi>Fame:</hi> ij. each celestial power. To bring their gifts to <hi>Ori╌a╌naes</hi> bower, to <hi>O╌rianaes</hi> bower. Then sang the shepherds &amp; Nymphs of <hi>Diana,</hi> Long liue faire <hi>Ori╌a╌na,</hi> faire <hi>Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>a╌na.</hi> Then sang the shepherds and Nymphs of <hi>Diana,</hi> Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na,</hi> faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na. a╌na,</hi> ij. faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na.</hi> Long liue faire <hi>Ori╌a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na,</hi> ij. ij. faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na,</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="23" type="song">
                        <pb facs="tcp:173820:64"/>
                        <head>Of 6. XXIII. <hi>QVINTVS.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <byline>Thomas Morley.</byline>
                        <p>
                           <gap reason="music">
                              <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                           </gap> HArd by a Cristall ij. foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na</hi> the bright, ij. lay downe a sleeping, The birds they finely cherped, ij. ij. ij. The windes were stilled, Sweetly with these accen╌ting, ij. The aire was fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, This is that faire whose head a crowne deserueth, Which heauen for her re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ser╌ueth, ij. Leaue shepherds your lambs keeping, ij. Vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the barren mountaine, ij. the barren mountaine, vpon &amp;c. And Nymphs attend on hir &amp; leaue your bowers. Then sang the shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herds and Nymphs, Nymphs of <hi>Di╌a╌na.</hi> ij. Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="24" type="song">
                        <pb facs="tcp:173820:65"/>
                        <head>Of 6 XXIIII. QVINTVS.</head>
                        <byline>Edward Iohnson.</byline>
                        <p>
                           <gap reason="music">
                              <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                           </gap> COme come blessed Bird, Come blessed Bird and with thy sugred rel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish, Help our declining quire now to em╌bellish, For Bonny bootes, ij. For Bonny bootes that so a loft would fetch it, that so aloft would fetch it, Oh he is dead and none of vs can reach it, and &amp;c. <hi>Elpin,</hi> for fault of bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter will serue in the <hi>Corus,</hi> Beegin and we will follow thee in order, in order. Then sang the Woodborne minstrell of <hi>Dia╌na,</hi> Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na.</hi> Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:173820:65"/>
                  <p>SEXTVS.</p>
                  <p>MADRIGALES The Triumphes of Oriana, to 5. and 6. voices: com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posed by diuers seuerall <hi>aucthors.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Newly published by Thomas Morley Batcheler of Musick, and one of the gentlemen of her</hi> Maiesties honorable Chappell.</p>
                  <p>1601.</p>
                  <p>IN LONDON PRINTED BY THOMAS ESTE, the assigne of Thomas Morley.</p>
                  <p>¶ Cum priuilegio Regiae Maiestatis.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="table_of_contents">
                  <pb facs="tcp:173820:66"/>
                  <head>¶ The Table of all the Madrigales contained in these bookes, vvith the names of their seuerall authors.</head>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Songs of 5. parts.</head>
                     <list>
                        <item>Hence Stars you dazell but the sight. <hi>Michaell Este.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>VVIth Angells face and brightnesse. I <hi>Daniell Norcome.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Lightly she whipped o're y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> dales. II <hi>Iohn Mundy Batcheler of Musick</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Long liue faire <hi>Oriana.</hi> III <hi>Ellis Gibbons.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>All creatures now are merry. IIII <hi>Iohn Benet.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Faire <hi>Oriana</hi> beauties Queene. V <hi>Iohn Hilton. Batcheler of Musick</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>The Nymphs and shepherds danced. VI <hi>George Marson. Batch. of Musick</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Calme was the Aire. VII <hi>Richard Carlton. Batch. of Musick</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Thus bonny bootes the birth day. VIII <hi>Iohn Holmes.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Sing shepherds all. IX <hi>Richard Nicolson.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>The Faunes and Satirs tripping. X <hi>Thomas Tomkins.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Come gentle swaines. XI <hi>Michaell Cauendish.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Withdraw your selues yee shepherds. XII <hi>William Cobbold.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Arise awake you silly shepherds sleping. XIII <hi>Thomas Morley Batch. of Musick</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Song of 6. parts.</head>
                     <list>
                        <item>Faire Nymphes I heard one telling. XIIII <hi>Iohn Farmer.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>The lady <hi>Oriana.</hi> XV <hi>Iohn Wilby.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Hark! hark, did you euer heare &amp;c. XVI <hi>Thomas Hunt. Batch. of Musick</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>As <hi>Ʋesta</hi> was from <hi>Latmos</hi> hill &amp;c. XVII <hi>Thomas Weelks.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Faire <hi>Orian</hi> in the morne. XVIII <hi>Iohn Milton.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Round about her Charret &amp;c. XIX <hi>Ellis Gibbons.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>With Angells face and brightnesse. XX <hi>George Kirbye.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Faire <hi>Oriana</hi> seeming to wink at folly. XXI <hi>Robert Iones.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Faire <hi>Citharea</hi> presents her Doues &amp;c. XXII <hi>Iohn Lisley.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Hard by a Christall fountaine. XXIII <hi>Thomas Morley. Batch. of Musick</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Come blessed Byrd &amp;c. XXIIII <hi>Edward Iohnson. Batch. of Musick</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
               <div type="dedication">
                  <pb facs="tcp:173820:66"/>
                  <head>TO THE RIGHT HO<seg rend="sup">norable</seg>. THE LORD Charles Howard <hi>Earle of Notingham, Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron</hi> of <hi>Effingham,</hi> Knight of the Noble order of the <hi>Garter,</hi> Lord high <hi>Admirall</hi> of <hi>England, Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and <hi>Wales, &amp;c.</hi> And one of her Majesties most honorable Priuie Counsell.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>RIGHT HO<seg rend="sup">norable</seg>.</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Haue aduentured to dedicate these few discordant tunes to be censured by the ingenious disposition of your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ships Honorable rare perfection, perswading my selfe, that these labours, composed by me and others, (as in the sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uey hereof, your Lordship may well perceiue) may not by any meanes passe, without the malignitie of some maliti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous <hi>Momus,</hi> whose malice (being as toothsome as the <hi>Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders</hi> sting) couched in the progres of a wayfayring mans passage, might make him retire though almost at his iourneyes end. Two speci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all <hi>Motiues</hi> haue imbouldened me (right Honorable) in this my proceeding. First, for that I consider, that as the body cannot bee without the shadow: so <hi>Homer</hi> (the Prince of Poets) may not be without a <hi>Zoilist:</hi> The second &amp; last is (the most forcible motiue) I know, (not onely by report, but also by experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment) your Lordship, to bee not onely <hi>Philomusus</hi> a louer of the <hi>Muses,</hi> and of learning: but <hi>Philomathes,</hi> a personage alway desirous, (though in all Arts sufficiently skilfull) to come to a more high perfection or <hi>Summum bonum.</hi> I will not trouble your Lordship with to to tedious circumstances, onely I humbly intreat your Lordship (in the name of many) to patronage this work with no lesse acceptance, then I with a willing and kinde hart dedicate it. So shall I think the <hi>initium</hi> of this worke not onely happely begun, but to bee <hi>finited</hi> with a more happie period.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Your Honours deuoted in all dutie, Thomas Morley.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div n="sextus" type="musical_part">
                  <div type="songs_of_six_parts">
                     <div n="14" type="song">
                        <pb facs="tcp:173820:67"/>
                        <pb facs="tcp:173820:67"/>
                        <head>Of 6. XIIII. SEXTVS.</head>
                        <byline>Iohn Farmer.</byline>
                        <p>
                           <gap reason="music">
                              <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                           </gap> FAire Nymphs I heard one telling, To beautifie the place, the place, to &amp;c. the place, The Faunes are running, are running, The shepherds their pipes tuneing, ij. To shew their cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, The Lambs amazed leaue of their grasing, And blind their eies, with gasing, whilst the earths Goddesse doth draw neere your places, Attended by the Muses, ij. and the Graces, the Graces. Then sang the shepherds and Nimphs, ij. of <hi>Di╌a╌na,</hi> Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na,</hi> ij. Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="15" type="song">
                        <pb facs="tcp:173820:68"/>
                        <head>Of 6. XV. SEXTVS.</head>
                        <byline>Iohn Wilbye.</byline>
                        <p>
                           <gap reason="music">
                              <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                           </gap> THe Lady <hi>Ori╌a╌na,</hi> ij. ij. Was dight ij. all in the treasures of <hi>Guiana,</hi> Was, ij. And on her Grace a thousand: ij. Graces tended, a thousand, ij. Graces tended, And thus sang they, faire Queene of peace &amp; plen╌ty, the fairest queene of twētie, Then with an Oliue wreath for peace renowned, for peace renowned, Her Virgins head they crowned; Which ceremony ended, ij. Which ceremo╌ny ended, ij. Vnto her Grace y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> thousād Graces bended. Then sang y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> shepherds &amp; Nimphs of <hi>Di╌a╌na,</hi> Long liue faire <hi>Ori╌a╌na,</hi> ij. ij. ij. Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na.</hi> ij. faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="16" type="song">
                        <pb facs="tcp:173820:68"/>
                        <head>Of 6. XVI. SEXTVS.</head>
                        <byline>Thomas Hunt.</byline>
                        <p>
                           <gap reason="music">
                              <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                           </gap> HArk! ij. ij. hark! ij. ij. did yee euer heare, did &amp;c. so sweet, so sweet a singing? ij did yee &amp;c. They sing young loue to wake, to wa╌ken, The Nymphs vnto the woods, ij. their Queene are bring╌ing, are bringing, There was a note well taken, there ij. O good! O most de╌uinely ditti'd, O most de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nine, O most deuinely ditti'd, A Queene &amp; song most ex╌cellent, most ex╌cellently fitted, most excellent, ij. most excellently fitted, I neuer saw a fayrer, I neuer heard a rarer, I neuer saw a fayrer, I neuer heard a ra╌rer, jj. Then sang the Nymphs &amp; shepherds of Di╌a╌na, Long liue faire O╌ri╌a╌na, ij. ij. Long liue faire O╌ri╌a╌na, faire O╌ri╌a╌na.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="17" type="song">
                        <pb facs="tcp:173820:69"/>
                        <head>Of 6. XVII. SEXTVS.</head>
                        <byline>Thomas Weelkes.</byline>
                        <p>
                           <gap reason="music">
                              <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                           <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S <hi>Vesta,</hi> ij. from <hi>Latmos</hi> hill descending, ij. She spied a maiden Queene ij. the same ascen╌ding, ascending, the same ascen╌ding, ascen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, Attended on by all the shepherds swain, ij. To whom <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anaes</hi> darlings, Came running down amaine, ij. Came running downe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine, ij. ij. ij. a╌maine, First two by two, and three by three to╌ge╌ther, Leauing their Goddesse, hasted thether, And mingling with the shepherds of her traine, With mirthfull tunes, ij. her presence enter╌taine, ij. Then sang the shepherds and
<pb facs="tcp:173820:69"/>
                           <gap reason="music">
                              <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                           </gap> Nymphs of <hi>Di╌a╌na,</hi> Nymphs of <hi>Di╌a╌na,</hi> Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na. O╌ri╌a╌na,</hi> ij. ij. Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na,</hi> ij. ij. ij. <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na.</hi> Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na,</hi> Long liue faire <hi>Ori╌a╌na,</hi> faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na.</hi> Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na,</hi> Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na,</hi> Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="18" type="song">
                        <pb facs="tcp:173820:70"/>
                        <head>Of 6. XVIII. SEXTVS.</head>
                        <byline>Iohn Milton.</byline>
                        <p>
                           <gap reason="music">
                              <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                           </gap> FAire <hi>Orian:</hi> With veluet steps on ground, which made nor print nor sound, Would see her Nymphs a bed, her: ij. what liues those Ladies led, those ij. what: ij. what: ij. those: ij. what: ij. The Roses blushing sayd, O stay, O stay thou shepherds mayd, O stay: ij. And on a sodaine all, they rose and heard her call, they: ij Then sang those shepherds and Nymphs of <hi>Di╌a╌na,</hi> then: ij Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na,</hi> Long: ij. faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na.</hi> Long: ij. faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="19" type="song">
                        <pb facs="tcp:173820:70"/>
                        <head>Of 6. XIX. SEXTVS.</head>
                        <byline>Ellis Gibbons.</byline>
                        <p>
                           <gap reason="music">
                              <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                           </gap> ROund about her Charret with all admiring strains, ij. The <hi>Hya╌des</hi> and <hi>Drya╌des</hi> ij. giue swestest entertaines, Lo how the gods, ij. Lo how the gods in reuells do ac╌cord, Whilst doth each goddesse melodies a╌fford, whilst doth each Goddesse melo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies a╌fford, Now <hi>Baccus</hi> is consorting, <hi>Amphions</hi> harp's reporting. To the shepherds pipes sing the Nymphs of <hi>Di╌a╌na,</hi> Long liue faire <hi>Ori╌a╌na.</hi> ij. Long liue faire <hi>Ori╌a╌na.</hi> Long liue faire <hi>O╌ria╌na.</hi> ij. ij.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="20" type="song">
                        <pb facs="tcp:173820:71"/>
                        <head>Of 6. XX. SEXTVS.</head>
                        <byline>George Kyrbie.</byline>
                        <p>
                           <gap reason="music">
                              <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                           </gap> WIth Angells face and brightnesse &amp; ori╌ent hew, faire <hi>Ori╌ana,</hi> ij. faire <hi>Ori╌ana</hi> shining, with nimble foote she tript, o're hils and mountaines, with nimble foot she tripped, o're hills and moūtains, At last in dale she rested, hard by <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anaes</hi> fountaines, <hi>Dia:</hi> ij This is that maiden Queene, of the Fairie land, With septer in her hand, ij. The Faunes &amp; Satirs dauncing, did shew their nimble lightnes, ij. &amp; brought their baskets full of herbs &amp; flow╌ers. Then sang y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> shepherds &amp; Nimphs of <hi>Di╌a╌na,</hi> Nymphs of <hi>Diana,</hi> Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌ana.</hi> ij. Lōg liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌ana,</hi> ij. Long liue faire <hi>Ori╌a╌na,</hi> ij.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="21" type="song">
                        <pb facs="tcp:173820:71"/>
                        <head>Of 6. XXI. SEXTVS.</head>
                        <byline>Robert Iones.</byline>
                        <p>
                           <gap reason="music">
                              <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                           </gap> FAire <hi>O╌ria╌na,</hi> ij. ij. seeming to winck at folly, at folly, Lay softly down, lay softly downe a sleeping, ij. ij. But hearing that the world was growen vnholly, to weeping, to weeping, So wakt, she sight, she sight, ij. and with crost armes, sate drincking teares for others harms. sate &amp;c. for o╌thers harmes. and shepherds of <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ana,</hi> ij. Long liue faire <hi>O╌ria╌na,</hi> faire <hi>Oriana,</hi> Long ij. ij. faire <hi>O╌ri╌ana,</hi> Long: ij. faire <hi>Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>a╌na,</hi> faire <hi>Ori╌a╌na.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="22" type="song">
                        <pb facs="tcp:173820:72"/>
                        <head>Of 6. XXII. SEXTVS.</head>
                        <byline>Iohn Lisley.</byline>
                        <p>
                           <gap reason="music">
                              <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                           </gap> FAire <hi>Citharea</hi> presents her Doues, ij. <hi>Minerua</hi> sweetly singeth, <hi>Ioue</hi> giues a crown, a garland <hi>Iuno</hi> bringeth, <hi>Fame</hi> summons each celest'all power, ij. To bring their gifts to <hi>O╌ri╌anaes</hi> bower, Then sang the shepherds &amp; Nymphs of <hi>Di╌a╌na,</hi> ij. Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na,</hi> ij. Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na.</hi> Then sang the shepherds &amp; Nymphs of <hi>Di╌a╌na,</hi> ij. Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>a╌na.</hi> ij. Long: liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na.</hi> ¶ faire <hi>Ori╌ana.</hi> Long &amp;c. faire <hi>Ori╌a╌na,</hi> Long liue faire <hi>Oria╌na,</hi> ij. ij. ij. ij.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="23" type="song">
                        <pb facs="tcp:173820:72"/>
                        <head>Of 6. XXIII. SEXTVS.</head>
                        <byline>Thomas Morley.</byline>
                        <p>
                           <gap reason="music">
                              <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                           </gap> HArd by a Cristall fountaine <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na</hi> the bright, Lay downe a sleeping, ij. The birds they finely chirped, ij. ij. The windes were stilled, were stilled. Sweetly with these accenting, ij. The aire was filled, ij. This is that faire whose head a crowne de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serueth, Which heauen for her reserueth, ij. leaue shepherds your lambs keeping, Vpon the barren mountaine, ij. the &amp;c. ij. For she the shepherds life maintaines and you╌ers. Then sang the shepherds and Nymphs Nymphs of <hi>Di╌a╌na,</hi> ij. <hi>Di╌a╌na,</hi> Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na,</hi> ij. Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na,</hi> ij. ij.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="24" type="song">
                        <pb facs="tcp:173820:73"/>
                        <head>Of 6 XXIIII. SEXTVS.</head>
                        <byline>Edward Iohnson.</byline>
                        <p>
                           <gap reason="music">
                              <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                           </gap> COme blessed: For Bonny bootes that so aloft would fetch it, that so a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loft would fetch it, that so aloft would fetch it, Oh he is dead and none of vs can reach it, and none of vs can reach it, And <hi>Dorus,</hi> for fault of better wil serue in the <hi>Corus,</hi> Begin and we will follow thee in order, in or╌der, Then sang the Woodborne minstrell of <hi>Di╌a╌na,</hi> Long liue, Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na.</hi> faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na</hi> Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na,</hi> Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:173820:73"/>
                  <p>BASSVS.</p>
                  <p>MADRIGALES The Triumphes of Oriana, to 5. and 6. voices: com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posed by diuers seuerall <hi>aucthors.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Newly published by Thomas Morley Batcheler of Musick, and one of the gentlemen of her</hi> Maiesties honorable Chappell.</p>
                  <p>1601.</p>
                  <p>IN LONDON PRINTED BY THOMAS ESTE, the assigne of Thomas Morley.</p>
                  <p>¶ Cum priuilegio Regiae Maiestatis.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="table_of_contents">
                  <pb facs="tcp:173820:74"/>
                  <head>¶ The Table of all the Madrigales contained in these bookes, vvith the names of their seuerall authors.</head>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Songs of 5. parts.</head>
                     <list>
                        <item>Hence Stars you dazell but the sight. <hi>Michaell Este.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>VVIth Angells face and brightnesse. I <hi>Daniell Norcome.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Lightly she whipped o're y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> dales. II <hi>Iohn Mundy Batcheler of Musick</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Long liue faire <hi>Oriana.</hi> III <hi>Ellis Gibbons.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>All creatures now are merry. IIII <hi>Iohn Benet.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Faire <hi>Oriana</hi> beauties Queene. V <hi>Iohn Hilton. Batcheler of Musick</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>The Nymphs and shepherds danced. VI <hi>George Marson. Batch. of Musick</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Calme was the Aire. VII <hi>Richard Carlton. Batch. of Musick</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Thus bonny bootes the birth day. VIII <hi>Iohn Holmes.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Sing shepherds all. IX <hi>Richard Nicolson.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>The Faunes and Satirs tripping. X <hi>Thomas Tomkins.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Come gentle swaines. XI <hi>Michaell Cauendish.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Withdraw your selues yee shepherds. XII <hi>William Cobbold.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Arise awake you silly shepherds sleping. XIII <hi>Thomas Morley Batch. of Musick</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Song of 6. parts.</head>
                     <list>
                        <item>Faire Nymphes I heard one telling. XIIII <hi>Iohn Farmer.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>The lady <hi>Oriana.</hi> XV <hi>Iohn Wilby.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Hark! hark, did you euer heare &amp;c. XVI <hi>Thomas Hunt. Batch. of Musick</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>As <hi>Ʋesta</hi> was from <hi>Latmos</hi> hill &amp;c. XVII <hi>Thomas Weelks.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Faire <hi>Orian</hi> in the morne. XVIII <hi>Iohn Milton.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Round about her Charret &amp;c. XIX <hi>Ellis Gibbons.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>With Angells face and brightnesse. XX <hi>George Kirbye.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Faire <hi>Oriana</hi> seeming to wink at folly. XXI <hi>Robert Iones.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Faire <hi>Citharea</hi> presents her Doues &amp;c. XXII <hi>Iohn Lisley.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Hard by a Christall fountaine. XXIII <hi>Thomas Morley. Batch. of Musick</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Come blessed Byrd &amp;c. XXIIII <hi>Edward Iohnson. Batch. of Musick</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
               <div type="dedication">
                  <pb facs="tcp:173820:74"/>
                  <head>TO THE RIGHT HO<seg rend="sup">norable</seg>. THE LORD Charles Howard <hi>Earle of Notingham, Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron</hi> of <hi>Effingham,</hi> Knight of the Noble order of the <hi>Garter,</hi> Lord high <hi>Admirall</hi> of <hi>England, Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and <hi>Wales, &amp;c.</hi> And one of her Majesties most honorable Priuie Counsell.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>RIGHT HO<seg rend="sup">norable</seg>.</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Haue aduentured to dedicate these few discordant tunes to be censured by the ingenious disposition of your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ships Honorable rare perfection, perswading my selfe, that these labours, composed by me and others, (as in the sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uey hereof, your Lordship may well perceiue) may not by any meanes passe, without the malignitie of some maliti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous <hi>Momus,</hi> whose malice (being as toothsome as the <hi>Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders</hi> sting) couched in the progres of a wayfayring mans passage, might make him retire though almost at his iourneyes end. Two speci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all <hi>Motiues</hi> haue imbouldened me (right Honorable) in this my proceeding. First, for that I consider, that as the body cannot bee without the shadow: so <hi>Homer</hi> (the Prince of Poets) may not be without a <hi>Zoilist:</hi> The second &amp; last is (the most forcible motiue) I know, (not onely by report, but also by experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment) your Lordship, to bee not onely <hi>Philomusus</hi> a louer of the <hi>Muses,</hi> and of learning: but <hi>Philomathes,</hi> a personage alway desirous, (though in all Arts sufficiently skilfull) to come to a more high perfection or <hi>Summum bonum.</hi> I will not trouble your Lordship with to to tedious circumstances, onely I humbly intreat your Lordship (in the name of many) to patronage this work with no lesse acceptance, then I with a willing and kinde hart dedicate it. So shall I think the <hi>initium</hi> of this worke not onely happely begun, but to bee <hi>finited</hi> with a more happie period.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Your Honours deuoted in all dutie, Thomas Morley.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div n="bassus" type="musical_part">
                  <div type="songs_of_five_parts">
                     <div type="song">
                        <pb facs="tcp:173820:75"/>
                        <head>Of 5. BASSVS.</head>
                        <byline>Michaell Este.</byline>
                        <p>
                           <gap reason="music">
                              <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                           </gap> HEnce Stars, ij. to dim of light, you dazel but the sight, you teach to grope by night, you dazel but y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> sight, you teach to grope by night, you dazell but y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> sight, you teach to grope by night, to: ij excelling you so far, Then <hi>Phebus</hi> wipt his eyes, wipt his eyes, and <hi>Zephir</hi> cleer'd the Skies, cleer'd the Skies, in sweet accented cries. Then sang the shepherds &amp; Nymphs of <hi>Dia╌na,</hi> Nymphs: ij. Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌ana,</hi> Long: ij. Long: liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>This song being sent to late, and all the other printed, I plast it before the rest, rather then to leaue it out.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="1" type="song">
                        <pb facs="tcp:173820:75"/>
                        <head>Of 5. I. BASSVS.</head>
                        <byline>Daniell Norcome.</byline>
                        <p>
                           <gap reason="music">
                              <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                           </gap> WIth Angels face and brightnesse, With nimble foote she trip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped, o're hills and mountaines, ij. ij. &amp; mountaines, Hard by <hi>Dia╌nas</hi> fountaines, This is that maiden <hi>Queene,</hi> of the Fayrie land, With scepter in her hand, ij. The Faunes and Satires dauncing, Did shew their nimble nimble lightnesse, And brought their baskets full of hearbs and flowers. Then sang the shepherds and Nimphs of <hi>Di╌a╌na,</hi> Long liue, Long liue faire <hi>Ori╌a╌na.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="2" type="song">
                        <pb facs="tcp:173820:76"/>
                        <head>Of 5. II. BASSVS.</head>
                        <byline>Iohn Mundy.</byline>
                        <p>
                           <gap reason="music">
                              <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                           <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>Ightly she: &amp;c. Gently she trode the flowres, the flowres, ij. And they as gently kist her tender feet, The birds in their best language bad her welcome, welcome, being proud that <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na</hi> heard their song: The cloue foot Satires singing, Made Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sick to the Faunes a daun╌cing, And both to gether with an emphasis, Sang <hi>O╌ri╌a╌nas</hi> prai╌ses, ij. whilst the aioyning woods with their melody, their melody, did entertaine their sweet, ij. their sweet harmony. Then sang the sheperds and Nimphes of <hi>Di╌a╌na,</hi> the Nimphes of <hi>Dia╌na,</hi> ij. ij.
<pb facs="tcp:173820:76"/>
                           <gap reason="music">
                              <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                           </gap> Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na,</hi> faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na.</hi> ij. ij. faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="3" type="song">
                        <pb facs="tcp:173820:77"/>
                        <head>Of 5. III. BASSVS.</head>
                        <byline>Ellis Gibbons.</byline>
                        <p>
                           <gap reason="music">
                              <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                           </gap> LOng liue faire <hi>Ori╌a╌na,</hi> Heark, did you euer heare so sweet a sing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, They sing young Loue to waken, The Nimphs vn╌to the woods, ij. their Queene are bringing, Ther was a note well taken, O good, Hark, how ioyfully, how ioyfully tis ditti'd, A Queene &amp; Song most excellent╌ly fitted, I neuer saw, ij. a fairer, I neuer heard a ra╌rer, Then sing ye Shepherds and Nimphs of <hi>Di╌a╌na,</hi> Nimphs of <hi>Di╌a╌na,</hi> Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na,</hi> Long liue, Long line faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na,</hi> Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na,</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="4" type="song">
                        <pb facs="tcp:173820:77"/>
                        <head>Of 5. IIII. BASSVS.</head>
                        <byline>Iohn Benet.</byline>
                        <p>
                           <gap reason="music">
                              <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                           </gap> ALL cre'tures now are merry merry merry {repeat} {repeat} {repeat} {repeat} {repeat} {repeat} minded, The shepherds daughters playing {repeat} The Nimphes are Fa la laing, {repeat} The Nimphs are Fa la la la la-ing, Yond bugle was wel winded, At <hi>O╌rianaes</hi> presence each thing smileth, The flowres themselues dis╌co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, {repeat} Birds ouer hir do houer, Musick the time beguileth, See wher she comes, {repeat} With flowry garlands crowned, Queene of all queenes re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowned, {repeat} Then sang the shepherds &amp; Nimphes of <hi>Diana,</hi> Nimphes of <hi>Diana,</hi> long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na,</hi> faire <hi>Oria╌na.</hi> Long {repeat} faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="5" type="song">
                        <pb facs="tcp:173820:78"/>
                        <head>Of 5. V. BASSVS.</head>
                        <byline>Iohn Hilton.</byline>
                        <p>
                           <gap reason="music">
                              <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                           </gap> FAire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na</hi> beauties Queene, faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na,</hi> {repeat} {repeat} beauties Queene, Tripped a long the verdant greene, a long the verdant greene, The Faunes and Satires, {repeat} running out, running out, Skipped and danced, {repeat} round a╌bout, {repeat} Flora forsooke hir painted bowrs, hir painted bowres, forsooke hir painted bowres, And made a Coronet of flowres. and &amp;c. Then sang the Nimphes of chast <hi>Di╌a╌na,</hi> {repeat} Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>a╌na,</hi> {repeat} faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na,</hi> Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na,</hi> Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="6" type="song">
                        <pb facs="tcp:173820:78"/>
                        <head>Of 5. VI. BASSVS.</head>
                        <byline>George Marson.</byline>
                        <p>
                           <gap reason="music">
                              <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                           </gap> THe Nimphs and shepheards daunced, Lauoltos in a dazy tapstred vally, Loue from their face lamps glaunced, Till wantonly they dally, {repeat} a Rose bankt ally, bright Maiestie aduanced, {repeat} {repeat} A crowne grac't Virgin whom all peo╌ple honor, all &amp;c. They leaue their sport amazed, Run all to, runne all to looke, run all to looke vpon hir, A moment scarce they gazed, Ere beauties splendor all their eies their eies had dazed, desire to see, yet e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer fixed on hir. Then sang the Shepherds &amp; Nimphs of <hi>Di╌ana,</hi> Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na,</hi> faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na.</hi> Liue long faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na,</hi> liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na,</hi> faire <hi>O╌ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>a╌na, O╌ri╌a╌na,</hi> Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="7" type="song">
                        <pb facs="tcp:173820:79"/>
                        <head>Of 5. VII. BASSVS.</head>
                        <byline>Richard Carlton.</byline>
                        <p>
                           <gap reason="music">
                              <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                           </gap> CAlme was the aire, and cleere the skye, Faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na</hi> passing by, Ouer the downes to I╌da plains ij. Wher heau'n born sisters with their traines, Did all attend hir sacred beauty, Striuing to excell in duty, Satirs and Nimphs ij. dauncing together, Shepherds triumphing, {repeat} flocking thether, Seeing their sou'raigne mistris ther, their so: &amp;c. That kept their flocks &amp; them from feare, That kept: &amp;c With hie strayn'd voice, And harts reioyce, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce. Thus sang the shepherds and Nimphs of <hi>Di╌a╌na,</hi> Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na,</hi> {repeat} Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na.</hi> {repeat}</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="8" type="song">
                        <pb facs="tcp:173820:79"/>
                        <head>Of 5. VIII. BASSVS.</head>
                        <byline>Iohn Holmes.</byline>
                        <p>
                           <gap reason="music">
                              <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                           </gap> THus bonny: Of her hes Lady deerest, {repeat} Faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na,</hi> which to his hart was neerest, The Nymphs &amp; shepherds feasted, With clowted creame were, {repeat} and to sing, and to sing were requested, {repeat} Loe heere the faire created (Quoth he) the worlds chiefe goddesse, Sing, then, {repeat} for she is Bonny boots sweet Mistres. Then sang the shepherds &amp; Nymphs of <hi>Di╌a╌na,</hi> the Nymphs of <hi>Di╌a╌na,</hi> Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na.</hi> {repeat} faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na,</hi> Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na, O╌ri╌a╌na,</hi> Long: &amp;c. faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="9" type="song">
                        <pb facs="tcp:173820:80"/>
                        <head>Of 5. IX. BASSVS.</head>
                        <byline>Richard Nicolson.</byline>
                        <p>
                           <gap reason="music">
                              <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                           </gap> SIng shepherds all, and in your roundelaies, and in: ij. and in your roundelaies, your roundelaies, Sing onely of faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌naes</hi> praise, sing onely of faire <hi>Ori╌a╌naes</hi> praise, The gods aboue will help to beare a part, The gods: ij. will help to beare a part, And men below, will trie their greatest art, and men below, will trye their greatest art, will: ij. Though neither gods nor men can well apply, can well apply, Though neither gods nor men can well apply, Fit song or tune to praise her worthely, Fit song or tune to praise her worthely, to praise her worthely. Then sang the shepherds, then: ij. then sang the shepherds, the shepherds, and Nimphs of <hi>Dia╌na,</hi> of <hi>Di╌a╌na,</hi>
                           <pb facs="tcp:173820:80"/>
                           <gap reason="music">
                              <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                           </gap> Long liue faire <hi>Ori╌a╌na,</hi> Long: ij. faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na,</hi> Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na.</hi> Long liue faire <hi>Ori╌a╌na,</hi> Then sang the shepherds, then sang the shepheards, then: ij. the shepherds, and Nymphs of <hi>Dia╌na,</hi> of <hi>Di╌a╌na,</hi> Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na.</hi> Long: ij. faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na.</hi> Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na,</hi> Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na,</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="10" type="song">
                        <pb facs="tcp:173820:81"/>
                        <head>Of 5. X. BASSVS.</head>
                        <byline>Thomas Tomkins.</byline>
                        <p>
                           <gap reason="music">
                              <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                           </gap> THE Faunes: With liuely Nymphs, ij. ij. Of fresh coole brookes, of: ij. of: ij. &amp; foun╌taines, And those of woods &amp; moūtaines, Like Roes came nimbly skiping, came: ij. skipping, By signes, ij. their mirth vnripping, their: ij. ij. My faire Queene, faire Queene, In peaces armes, With <hi>Amaltheas</hi> twentie, twentie, Brim full of welthie plentie, And still to giue frequented, and still: ij. With bare gifts not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented, not: ij. The de╌my gods, pray to the gods supernall, supernall, the gods: ij. the: ij. Her life, Her wealth, her fame, may be Eter╌nall. Her life, Her wealth, Her fame, Her life: ij. may be Eternall, may: ij.
<pb facs="tcp:173820:81"/>
                           <gap reason="music">
                              <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                           </gap> be Eternall. Then sang the shepherds &amp; Nimphs of <hi>Di╌a╌na,</hi> and: ij. &amp;: ij. faire <hi>O╌ri╌ana.</hi> faire <hi>O╌ri╌ana.</hi> faire: ij Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na,</hi> Long: ij.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="11" type="song">
                        <pb facs="tcp:173820:82"/>
                        <head>Of 5. XI. BASSVS.</head>
                        <byline>Michaell Cauendish.</byline>
                        <p>
                           <gap reason="music">
                              <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                           </gap> COme gentle swaines and shepherds daintie daughters, adornd with curtesie, come gentle swains &amp; shepherds dainty, dainty daughters adornd with curtesie &amp; comely du╌ties, Come sing and ioy and grace with loue, with louely laugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, The birth day of the beauties, of beauties. Then sang the Shepherds and Nymphs of <hi>Di╌a╌na,</hi> of <hi>Di╌a╌na,</hi> Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na,</hi> Long liue, Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na.</hi> {repeat} Then sang the shepherds and Nymphs of <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>a╌na,</hi> of <hi>Di╌a╌na,</hi> Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na,</hi> Long liue, Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na.</hi> {repeat}</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="12" type="song">
                        <pb facs="tcp:173820:82"/>
                        <head>Of 5. XII. BASSVS.</head>
                        <byline>William Cobbold.</byline>
                        <p>
                           <gap reason="music">
                              <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                           </gap> WIthdraw your selues ye shepherds from your bowres, And straw the path with flowrs, the Nimphs are comming, Sweetly the birds are chirping, are chirping, the swift beasts running, ij. ij. As all amaz'd they stand, still gazing, To see such bright stars blazing, hir daintie daughter leading, ij. The powres deuine to hir doe vale their bonnets, Prepare your selues to found your past'rall sonnets, ij. to sound your past'rall sonnets. Then sang the shepherds &amp; Nimphes of <hi>Di╌a╌na,</hi> Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na,</hi> ij. Long: ij Long: ij. Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na,</hi> Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na,</hi> faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="13" type="song">
                        <pb facs="tcp:173820:83"/>
                        <head>Of 5. XIII. BASSVS.</head>
                        <byline>Thomas Morley.</byline>
                        <p>
                           <gap reason="music">
                              <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                           </gap> ARise: Deuise, some honour for her sake by mirth to banish weep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, by mirth to banish weeping, Loe where she comes, A Prince, {repeat} of beauty rich and rare, for her delighting, Pretends to goe a Maying, You stately Nymphs draw neere, and strew your pathes with Ro╌ses, with Roses, Then sang the shepherds and Nimphs of <hi>Di╌a╌na,</hi> Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na,</hi> {repeat} Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na.</hi> Then sang:</p>
                     </div>
                     <trailer>Heere endeth the songs of fiue parts.</trailer>
                  </div>
                  <div type="songs_of_six_parts">
                     <div n="14" type="song">
                        <pb facs="tcp:173820:83"/>
                        <head>Of 6. XIIII. BASSVS.</head>
                        <byline>Iohn Farmer.</byline>
                        <p>
                           <gap reason="music">
                              <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                           </gap> FAire Nymphs ij. I heard one telling, Faire Nymphs I heard one telling, The Faunes are running, are running, ij. The shepherds their pipes tuneing, their: ij. The Lambs amazed leaue of their grasing, And blind their eies, with gasing, whilst the earths Goddesse, Goddesse, doth draw neere your pla╌ces, Attended by the Muses, ij. and the Graces, the Graces. Then sang the shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herds, ij. ij. of <hi>Di╌a╌na,</hi> Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na.</hi> ij.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="15" type="song">
                        <pb facs="tcp:173820:84"/>
                        <head>Of 6. XV. BASSVS.</head>
                        <byline>Iohn Wilbye.</byline>
                        <p>
                           <gap reason="music">
                              <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                           </gap> THe Lady <hi>Ori╌a╌na,</hi> Was dight all in the treasures of <hi>Guiana,</hi> ij. And on her Grace a thousand: ij. Graces tended, And thus sang they, faire Queene of peace &amp; plenty, the fairest queene of twētie, Thē with an Oliue wreath for peace renowned, Her Virgins head they crowned; ij. Which ceremony ended, ij. Vnto her Grace y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> thousād Graces bended. Then sang the shepherds &amp; Nymphs of <hi>Dia╌na,</hi> Long liue faire <hi>Ori╌a╌na,</hi> ij. faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na.</hi> Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na.</hi> ij. Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="16" type="song">
                        <pb facs="tcp:173820:84"/>
                        <head>Of 6. XVI. BASSVS.</head>
                        <byline>Thomas Hunt.</byline>
                        <p>
                           <gap reason="music">
                              <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                           </gap> HArk! ij. ij. hark! hark, did yee e╌uer heare, did &amp;c. so sweet a singing? ij. so sweet a singing? They sing young loue to waken, to wak en, The Nymphs vnto the woods their Queene are bringing, ij. their Queene are bringing, There was a note well taken, O good, hark hark: O good: O most deuine, O most deuinely ditti'd, A Queene and song most excel╌lently fitted, ij. ij. most ex╌cellently fitted, I neuer saw a fai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer, a fairer, Then sang the Nymphs and shepherds of <hi>Di╌a╌na,</hi> Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na,</hi> ij. Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na,</hi> Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na.</hi> ij.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="17" type="song">
                        <pb facs="tcp:173820:85"/>
                        <head>Of 6. XVII. BASSVS.</head>
                        <byline>Thomas Weelkes.</byline>
                        <p>
                           <gap reason="music">
                              <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                           <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S <hi>Vesta</hi> was, &amp;c. Attended on by all the shepherds swaine, To whom <hi>Dianaes</hi> dar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, Came running downe amaine, ij. Came running downe amaine, amaine, ij. came running downe amaine, then three by three together, Leauing their Goddesse, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sted thether, And mingling with the shepherds of her traine, With mirthfull tunes, her presence entertaine, her presence entertaine. Then sang the shepherds and Nymphs of <hi>Di╌a╌na,</hi> Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na.</hi> Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na,</hi> Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na,</hi> Long
<pb facs="tcp:173820:85"/>
                           <gap reason="music">
                              <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                           </gap> liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na,</hi> faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="18" type="song">
                        <pb facs="tcp:173820:86"/>
                        <head>Of 6. XVIII. BASSVS.</head>
                        <byline>Iohn Milton.</byline>
                        <p>
                           <gap reason="music">
                              <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                           </gap> FAire <hi>Orian:</hi> With vel╌uet steps on ground, which made nor print nor sound, Would see her Nymphs a bed, what liues those Ladies led, those ij. those: ij. what: ij. what: ij. what: ij. The Roses blushing sayd, O stay thou shepherds mayd, O stay: ij. And on a sodaine all, they rose and heard her call. Then sang those shepherds and Nymphs of <hi>Di╌a╌na,</hi> then: ij. Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na,</hi> Long: ij. Long: ij.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="19" type="song">
                        <pb facs="tcp:173820:86"/>
                        <head>Of 6. XIX. BASSVS.</head>
                        <byline>Ellis Gibbons.</byline>
                        <p>
                           <gap reason="music">
                              <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                           </gap> ROund about her Charret with all admiring strains, The <hi>Hyades</hi> and <hi>Drya╌des</hi> The <hi>Drya╌des,</hi> and <hi>Hya╌des,</hi> giue sweetest entertaines, ij. Lo how the gods in reuells, reuels do accord, accord, Whilst doth each goddes melodies afford, afford, whilst doth each goddesse melo: melodies afford, (O looke) Now <hi>Baccus</hi> is conforting, <hi>Sil╌uanus</hi> falls a sporting, <hi>Amphions</hi> harp's reporting. To the shepherds pipes sing y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Nymphs of <hi>Diana,</hi> Long liue faire <hi>Oriana.</hi> ij. Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na.</hi> ij. Long liue faire <hi>Ori╌a╌na.</hi> ij. faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="20" type="song">
                        <pb facs="tcp:173820:87"/>
                        <head>Of 6. XX. BASSVS.</head>
                        <byline>George Kyrbie.</byline>
                        <p>
                           <gap reason="music">
                              <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                           </gap> WIth Angells face: Faire <hi>Ori╌an╌a</hi> shining, With nimble foote she tripped, with nimble foot she tripped, o're hills and moūtains, At last in dale she rested, hard by <hi>Dianaes</hi> fountaines, <hi>Dia:</hi> ij. With septer in her hand, ij. The Faunes &amp; Satirs dauncing, did shew their nimble lightnes, Fairie <hi>Nais</hi> and the Nymphs, did leaue their bowers. Then sang the shepherds &amp; Nimphs of <hi>Di╌a╌na,</hi> Nymhs of <hi>Di╌a╌na,</hi> Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na,</hi> ij. Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌ana,</hi> ij. Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na,</hi> ij.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="21" type="song">
                        <pb facs="tcp:173820:87"/>
                        <head>Of 6. XXI. BASSVS.</head>
                        <byline>Robert Iones.</byline>
                        <p>
                           <gap reason="music">
                              <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                           </gap> FAire <hi>Oria╌na:</hi> Lay softly down a sleeping, Lay: ij. But hearing y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> the world was growen vnholly, her rest was turnd to weeping, to weeping, So wakt, so wakt, she sight, ij. ij. ij. &amp; with crost armes, sate drincking teares for others harms. and shepherds of <hi>Diana,</hi> and ij. Long liue faire <hi>Oria╌na,</hi> Long ij. Long: ij. Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="22" type="song">
                        <pb facs="tcp:173820:88"/>
                        <head>Of 6. XXII. BASSVS.</head>
                        <byline>Iohn Lisley.</byline>
                        <p>
                           <gap reason="music">
                              <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                           </gap> FAire <hi>Citharea</hi> presents her Doues, <hi>Miner╌ua</hi> sing╌eth, <hi>Ioue</hi> giues a crown, a garland <hi>Iuno</hi> bringeth, a garland: ij. <hi>Fame</hi> sumōd each ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lest'all power, <hi>Fame:</hi> ij. To bring their gifts to <hi>O╌ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anaes</hi> bower, to <hi>O╌ri╌anaes</hi> bower. Then sang y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> shepherds &amp; Nymphs of <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>a╌na,</hi> Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na,</hi> faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na,</hi> Then sang the shepherds &amp; Nymphs of <hi>Dia╌na,</hi> Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌ana,</hi> faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="23" type="song">
                        <pb facs="tcp:173820:88"/>
                        <head>Of 6. XXIII. BASSVS.</head>
                        <byline>Thomas Morley.</byline>
                        <p>
                           <gap reason="music">
                              <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                           </gap> HArd by a Cristall: The birds they finely chirped, ij. ij the birds they finely cherped, The windes were stilled, Sweetly with these accenting, ij. The aire was filled, Which heauen for her reserueth, ij. Leaue shepherds your lambs keeping, Vpon the barren mountaine, the &amp;c. Vpon &amp;c. for she the shepherds life maintaines and you<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers. Then sang the shepherds and Nymphs, Nymphs of <hi>Di╌a╌na.</hi> ij. Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na,</hi> faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na,</hi> Long &amp;c. faire <hi>Ori╌a╌na.</hi> Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na,</hi> faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na.</hi> Long &amp;c. faire <hi>Ori╌a╌na.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="24" type="song">
                        <pb facs="tcp:173820:89"/>
                        <head>Of 6 XXIIII. BASSVS.</head>
                        <byline>Edward Iohnson.</byline>
                        <p>
                           <gap reason="music">
                              <desc>〈♫〉</desc>
                           </gap> COme blessed: For Bonny bootes that so aloft would fetch it, ij. Oh he is dead, he is dead, and none of vs can reach it, ij. Then tune to vs sweet Bird thy shrill recorder, <hi>Elpin,</hi> and I and <hi>Dorus,</hi> for fault of better wil serue in the <hi>Corus,</hi> Begin and we will follow thee in order, in order. Then sang the Woodborne minstrell of <hi>Di╌a╌na,</hi> Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na.</hi> Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na.</hi> ij. Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na,</hi> ij. Long liue faire <hi>O╌ri╌a╌na.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
                  <pb facs="tcp:173820:89"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:173820:90"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:173820:90"/>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>